human and physical communities to switch levels where we can supply foodmouths and vegan foods and overcome hunger need.
human and physical communities to switch levels where we can supply foodmouths and vegan foods and overcome hunger need.
Director Wang Jin-mo plans to present project into the best possible outcome ofana
Director Wang Jin-mo plans to present project into the best possible outcome ofana
miss of knowledge in september
9月份的知識的想念
So today we're talking about the tax system
那麼今天我們討論的是稅制的問題
So, I wonder if you have noticed that in July this year
那麼各位不知道有沒有注意到今年7月的時候
Sino-British Institute puts forward a proposal for tax reform
中英研究院提出了一份稅制改革的建議書
Then this proposal has aroused a very wide discussion
那麼這一份建議書引起非常廣泛的討論
Well there's a lot of detail in it
那麼其中有很多細節
no way to report them all here i think
沒辦法在這裡一一報告我想
this
這個
part of the tax reform proposal
稅制改革建議書的其中有一部分
It's already fermenting
已經開始在發酵了
Especially in the sale and purchase of houses, etc.
尤其是在房屋的買賣等等
You can see this related issue
這相關的問題上各位可以看得出來
Well, it's already fermenting
那麼已經開始在發酵了
be directly or indirectly affected by it
直接或間接那麼會受到它的影響
The main moderator of this proposal is Academician Wang Ping in the United States
這份建議書主要的主持人是在美國的王平院士
The person in charge in Taiwan is the specific researcher Peng Xinkun present here.
在台灣的負責人就是在座的彭信坤特定研究員
he is here this year
他今年在場
Well, some of them are also Yang Jiancheng present here.
那麼其中有一部分也是在座的楊建成
identification
特定
already responsible
就已經負責了
Colleagues feel that Taiwan's tax system
同仁們有感以臺灣的稅制
There have been quite a few problems with the structure for a long time
長期以來結構出現相當多的問題
There are also quite a few unfair issues
也有相當多的不公平的問題
And the most important thing is that the taxman's lies are too strong
而且最重要的是稅員偽說太厲害
make the government unable to have enough power
使得政府沒辦法有足夠的力量
to do what should be done public
來做應該做的公共的
or aspects of welfare
或是福利的各方面的這個措施
The government's administrative tools have also been severely shot
政府的施政工具也被嚴重的打射了
So it's a very complex and very difficult problem
所以這是一個非常複雜也非常難的問題
worthy of further discussion
值得我們再進一步討論
Today we invite the Academia Sinica
今天我們邀請到中央研究院
Special Review Fellow at the Institute of Economics
經濟學研究所的特評研究員
Professor Yang Jiancheng came to give a lecture
楊建成教授來主講
Professor Yang is a very distinguished economist
楊教授是一位非常傑出的經濟學家
I think anyone here who has a major in economics knows
我想在座如果有經濟專業的人都知道
he is an excellent economist
他是很傑出的經濟學家
He is in this
他除了是他在這個
Virginia Politec
Virginia Politec
It's the school where Koreans shot and killed a lot of people
就是韓國人開槍殺死很多人的學校
He is Virginia Polytech's 1989
他是Virginia Polytech的1989年
PhD
起的博士學位
Then go back to Academia Sinica
然後就回中研院
Has been serving the contract
一直服務契經
In addition to being a member of the Institute of Economics, Academia Sinica
他除了是中研院經濟所的
Outside of Terby Fellows
特畢研究員以外
It is also an official university finance department
同時也是正式大學財政系的
Chair Professor
講座教授
His specialty is public economics
他的專長是公共經濟學
and political economy
和政治經濟學
Professor Wan from Academia Sinica
完教授從中研院
From associate researcher to special researcher
從副研究員研究員到特畢研究員
He has received many important academic honors
他得過許多重要的學術榮譽
Including Ministry of Education Academic Award 1994
包括教育部學術獎1994年
Including three NSC End Research Awards
包括三次國科會結束研究獎
including the National Science Council's 2002
包括國科會的2002年的
Extraordinary research awards and more
特畢研究獎金等等
so he is a
所以他是一位
medal-filled economist
灌滿勳章的經濟學學者
A topic he is going to talk about today
他今天要講的一個題目
in fact it is important
事實上是很重要的
Income tax versus consumption tax
就是所得稅 versus消費稅
So as we prepare this
那麼在我們籌備這個
tax reform
付稅改革
time for tax reform proposals
就是稅制改革建議書的時候
there is an academician
有一個院士
Fellows in the United States
在美國的院士
He just thinks
他就直接認為
GST should be used as a starting point
應該用消費稅起點
Others are of course this opinion is too strong
其他人是當然這個意見太過激烈
Didn't get everyone's credit
並沒有獲得大家的財信
So these issues are very complicated
所以這些問題非常的複雜
we now use applause
我們現在用掌聲
Welcome Professor Yang Jiancheng to us
歡迎楊建成教授給我們
Thank you all for coming
謝謝大家來參加
this time the speech
這一次的演講
i just mentioned that
我剛剛提到就是說
I am Berzene Tech B.Ed
我是Berzene Tech B.Ed
It was a Korean who killed many people
是一個韓國人殺了很多人
Later my junior college
後來我那個學弟學院
tell me
告訴我說
because of that
因為那件事情
Make our school more famous
讓我們學校更加有名
So in the future recruit new students
所以以後在招數新生上
Yellow tuna is more active
黃鮪是更踴躍
It might not have been that famous
本來可能沒那麼大的名氣
for killing a bunch of people
因為殺了一堆人
So it becomes more famous
所以名氣變得比較大
So everyone is more enthusiastic about yellow tuna
所以大家黃鮪更踴躍
Thank you all for coming
謝謝大家來參加
That is to say, let’s talk about it a little bit wider than this.
就是說就是稍微比這個稍微廣一點來談一下
But let me talk about an idea about a center
不過我談來談去大概一個中心的一個想法
So Luo Rui is not a very good Rui in Taiwan
就是索羅瑞在台灣並不是一個很好的瑞
not very good ray
並不是很好的瑞
We'll get to that in a minute but it has a lot of problems
我們等一下會談到就是它有很多問題
Well Sorori is not very good Ray
那麼索羅瑞不是很好的瑞
So is it possible to subsidize or help this Rui with other Rui?
那麼是不是可以用其他瑞來補助或幫助這個瑞
It’s probably a central issue that I’m going to talk about today.
大概就是我今天大概我整個要講的一個中心的一個問題
I'll probably talk about why Solori isn't that good
我大概會談一下索羅瑞為什麼不是那麼好
Why it is possible to use other ri to help or subsidize the words of sorori
為什麼可能用其他的瑞來幫助或補助索羅瑞的話
Maybe we can make our Rui characters better
可能可以讓我們的瑞字更好一點
What I just said is that what I probably talked about is not just about this
我剛剛講就是說我大概談的不是只針對這個
I'm probably a little wider
我大概稍微廣一點
I would like to mention some information now
我現在要提一下幾個資料
I probably won't say it, you should know
我大概不說 各位應該曉得
It's our debt
就是我們的債務未嘗云語
This is where we equal the central
這個是在我們等於中央
we last time
我們上次那個
It was just mentioned by Wang Wu
就是剛剛王武提到
He has this picture in the report
就報告書裡面他就有這個圖
you can draw that is to say
你可以畫得到就是說
our words in 81
我們在81年的話
He takes that as the unit
他這個以那個造為單位
Look at the words in 1981
你看在81年的話
about 0 years 57
大概0年57
In other words, about 0.5 megabytes
換句話說大概0.5兆左右
you can draw that is to say
你畫得到就是說
whose time passes
誰的時間經過的話
You can draw me higher and higher
你畫得到我越來越高
Now it's about 5 trillion
現在大概到5兆多
Some people say this is not very accurate
有人說這個還不是很準
Because it also includes, for example, some
因為還包括譬如說一些
old insurance loss catholic
老保的虧損 公教的
future problems
將來那些問題
But dare not do anything
不過不敢怎麼樣
tell us here
這裡就告訴我們說
You see, this growth rate is quite fast.
你看這個成長速度是還滿快的
And you see he is going up
而且你看他是向上走
how about going backwards
往後走是怎麼樣
We are now roughly every year
我們現在大概每年大概
about every year
大概每年大概有
The one from 200 billion to 300 billion is equal to
2000億到3000億的那個等於是
Equal to insufficient tax or other income
等於是稅收或是其他收入不足
In other words, among our expenditures
換句話我們的支出當中
probably probably
大概有大概
200 to 300 billion
2000到3000億
It depends on our year
就看我們那一年的
tax good bad bad
稅收好壞壞
don't remember good words
不要緊記好的話
tax is better
稅收就比較好
Remember that when you are poor, your taxes are poor.
緊記差的時候稅收就比較差
But probably as short as
不過大概就短少到
200 to 300 billion
2000到3000億
The ratio is the same
這個比重的話也是一樣
If this proportion
這個比重的話
That is to say, he is here
就是說他這個在
The average proportion of GDP in terms of the previous three years
前三年名目的GDP的平均比重
you see you know
你一看你知道
is also an upward
也是一個在向上走
if you go up
向上走的話
You see, it was around 13:00 at the beginning
你看剛開始的時候大概13點多
Now the word is probably in
現在的話大概是在
in a short period of time
短短的期間裡面
Now about 3 times and 4 times more
現在大概3倍4倍多
to 37 o'clock
到37點多
this number
這個數字
i think it's ok
我想還好
better than the rest of the world
跟全世界其他國家還好
But the worry is that this trend
但擔心的是這個趨勢
that trend
那個趨勢
This trend means
這個趨勢就是說
It is equivalent to more than thirty-seven points from a total amount
等於是從一個總量來看就三十七點多的話
You are better than other countries in the world
你跟全世界其他國來比的話都還好
Like Japan, it is more than 100%
像日本的話它是超過百分之一百的
better than many other countries
跟其他很多國家來比都好
But its rising figures make us more worried
但是它的上升數字上是讓我們比較擔心的
we are more worried
我們比較擔心的
ok this is what we mean
ok 這個就是我們就是說
My tax burden ratio in recent years
我過近年來的租稅負擔比例
This is also what we have in the report of the Central Committee
這個也是我們在那個中央的報告書上就有的
Probably you can draw until about eleven or twelve
大概你可以畫到就是說大概十一十二之間
Probably since 1991
大概就是九十一年開始
this number
這個數字
How does it compare to other countries?
假如跟其他國家來比的話大概是怎麼樣
let's take a look
我們來看一下
This is probably how many countries we have
這是大概是我們有幾個國家
Take a look like the Republic of China and the United States
像中華民國、美國看一下
What we say in Taiwan is probably like what we just said
像我們台灣的話大概像剛剛講的話
Since 1991, it has been around eleven o'clock
從九十一年開始大概就十一點多
In the past it was higher
在過去的話就比較高
It's after fifteen o'clock
十五點多等等
You can see and go down slowly
你可以看到就慢慢的往下走
go down slowly
慢慢往下走
It includes A and B
它有包括A跟B
A and B
A跟B
Because if it's past 12 o'clock
因為這12點多的話
That doesn't include us, for example, paying some annuities
還不包括我們譬如說繳了一些年金
paid some health insurance fees
繳了一些健保費用
because other countries
因為其他國家的話
Annuity payments are basically part of a tax
像年金繳的基本上也是一種稅的一部分
the annuity you pay the health insurance you pay
你繳的年金你繳的健保費用
basically
基本上
But let's split it into two columns
不過我們把它分成兩欄就對了
As far as column A is concerned
就A欄的話
Just doesn't include social security contributions
就是不包括社會安全捐
including not including annuity
就包括沒有包括年金
health insurance not included
沒有包括健保
This V course includes
這個V然的話就包括
If you look at the comparison
你看看比較起來的話
Even if we look at it with Vran
我們即使用V然來看的話
Compared with other countries
跟其他國家來比的話
like in Japan, to the twenties
像日本的話到二十幾
Thirty in German
德國的話到三十幾
words of anglicization
英國化國的話
Anyway, you talk to France to more than ten
反正你跟法國的話到十幾
Nordic countries
北歐那些國家
are full height
都是滿高的
Now I think Taiwan has a big problem
台灣現在我覺得有一個蠻大的問題
That is to say, the people have quite high unreasonable demands on society.
就是說民眾對社會無理的要求蠻高的
I hope the government will provide a lot of social welfare
希望政府提供很多的社會福利
But it's hard on angle tax
但在角稅上的話都很難
This is not unreasonable
這個也不是沒有道理
not without reason
也不是沒有道理
This is equivalent to the problem of a single machine
這個等於機身單單機的問題
For example, if you talk about Taiwan Telecom
譬如說你台電的話
you want to raise your electricity price
你要調高你的電價
In the case of CNPC, if the oil price is raised
中油的話 調高油價的話
It is often said that
常常聽到的言論就是說
you put some of your internal
你先把你內部的一些
Fluctuating line draft without calculation
沒有計較的波動線稿
Let’s fix the problem of the single machine first.
先弄好 這個機身單單機的問題
This is not so clear anymore
這個已經就不是那麼清楚了
But if we are comparing
不過我們在比較的話
Probably except for comparisons like Singapore
大概除了像新加坡這種比較
is special like city-state outside
就是特殊的像城市國家之外
Probably much lower
大概就低很多了
you can take a look
你可以看一看
That is to say, it is not very high
就是說就不是很高
but then again
但話說回來
Although this proportion is not very high
這個比重雖然是不是很高
But who will bear the burden?
但是負擔的人是哪些人負擔呢
I don't think this is as low as I thought.
這個我覺得沒有想像中那麼低
We know that Taiwan's
我們曉得現在台灣的
If there is a sleeping system, you should be small, including sleeping.
一個睡制的話 你們包括睡就應該小的
including sleeping when reporting to sleep
包括睡覺 在報睡的時候
you just go online
你就上網去就是說
For example, your buckle feet are flat
譬如說你的扣腳平單
when you report to sleep
等於你報睡的時候
He will automatically tell you how many hands you have
他自動就會當肉說你有多少手的
where did those hands come from
那些手的怎麼來的
They all come with a single buckle.
都是有一個扣腳平單來的
Is it flattened?
是不是扣腳平單呢
there is a ser party
就是有一個ser party
there is a third person in english
用英文來說有第三人
you work for a certain company
你再某一家公司工作
when the company pays you for water first
公司付給你先水的時候
He just pays you the first part of the water
他就把你付給你的先水那一部分
report him to, say, the IRS
把他報到譬如說國稅局去
The IRS has that information.
國稅局就掌握到那個資料
let's wait and see
我們等一下看看
Taiwan has a structural problem
台灣有一個結構性的問題
That is, there are many small and medium-sized enterprises in Taiwan.
就是台灣的中小企業很多
SMEs this thing
中小企業這個東西
It's like being your own boss
等於是自己當老闆
The function of this ser party is not lost
這個ser party的這個功能就沒有掉
otherwise it means
不然就是說
To be able to hold your hand
才能不能夠掌握到你的手的
Why can I get
為什麼能夠掌到
just through this ser party
就透過這個ser party
just define
就定義
When you pay your salary in that company
就你再那個公司付給你薪水的時候
He reported this information to the Ministry of Finance.
他就把這個訊息報到財政部去
or when the company pays you a bonus
或公司付給你紅利的時候
They know that a lot of people don't have this social party
他們曉得很多是沒有這個社會派對
For example, Sale Impointment
譬如說Sale Impointment
Now that you're the boss, he won't have this social party
你這一當老闆他就沒有這個社會派對
So this probably won't go away.
所以這個大概就沒有掉了
So you see that the tax rate seems to be very high
所以你看到這個稅率好像是不是很高
But it is believed that most
但是可以相信大概大部分
Most of it is due to the exchange of salary
很大部分都是薪資所的在互當
So this is not very high
所以這個算算不是很高
But if you count it on the payroll
但是假如你把它算到薪資所的身上的話
Maybe not as low as imagined
可能就沒有想像那麼低
not as low as imagined
沒有想像那麼低
This is also a big problem
這個也是一個滿大的問題
Then let's see
然後我們來看一下
That is to say, this is one of the pictures just now. Take a look.
就是說這個是剛剛那個圖的一個看一下
Basically you can draw to get us is very low
基本上你可以畫得到我們是很低的
In other words the size of our government
換句話說我們的政府規模
Compared with other countries, it is very low.
國家來比的話是很低的
very low
很低的
Yes Japan
有日本
look and compare
你看比較一下
like danish words
像丹麥的話
denmark like nordic countries words
丹麥像北歐國家的話
at 50 is really over 50
在50真是超過50
This is normal in the West
這個是西中平常
So their social welfare is doing well
所以他們社會福利辦得很好
not without reason
也不是沒有道理
because in your hand
因為你的手的當中
most are taxed
大部分都要繳稅
pay taxes
繳稅
But Taiwan's problem is
但台灣的問題就是
pay little tax
繳的稅不多
but hope that the government will provide high welfare
但又希望政府提供很高的福利
This gap creates a big problem
這個gap就造成很大的一個問題
OK
OK
this is
這個是
Of course, Taiwan now has another problem, that is,
台灣現在當然是有另外一個問題就是說
equal to
等於是
A problem of uneven distribution
分配不均的一個問題
This is of course from before
這個當然是從以前
You see what it says here
你看它這裡就是說
The board with the highest hand and the back of the board with the lowest
最高手的板子我們跟最低板子的背式
on the rise
在上升
this rise
這個上升
of course you can draw
當然你可以畫得到
somewhat likely to be exaggerated
有點可能會被誇大
a bit exaggerated
有點會誇大
The main reason is that you can draw
主要原因就是說你可以畫得到
in the early days
在早期的時候
that population
那個人口
It is not the same as the later population structure
跟後來的人口結構是不大一樣
For example, in the early days, it may have been a relatively large family.
譬如說早期的話可能都是一個比較大家庭的
Smaller family now
現在比較小家庭的
Everyone wants to say that my hands are already taller.
大家想說我手的本來就比較高
so this may be an exaggeration
所以這個可能會誇大
But the main problem is that
不過主要問題就是說
You can see that the trend is indeed going up
你可以看到這個趨勢的確在上升
However, the upward trend
不過話說這個上升趨勢
It's not a phenomenon of Taiwan retreating
不是台灣退了現象
This phenomenon occurs in many countries around the world
全世界的很多國家都有這個現象
Let's look at the picture below
我們看一下下面這個圖
This picture is also interesting
這個圖也是有趣的
It is in the information of your Doctrine
就是你主義處的資料當中
Among the materials of the Doctrine of Doctrine
主義處的資料當中
It puts equal to a lock among
它把等於一個鎖的當中
It is mainly divided into two parts
它主要分了兩部分
part of what we see here
一部分就是我們這裡看到的
remuneration for bereavement
受故人緣的報酬
The general salary is the salary for the deceased
受故人緣報酬就一般的薪水
normal salary
一般薪水
There are other locks
還有就是其他的鎖的
Other locks include profits earned by the company
其他鎖的包括公司賺的利潤
and interest
還有利息等等
Anyway, other locks
反正就其他鎖的
ground rent etc.
地租等等
This is collectively called operating surplus
這個統稱就叫營業營餘
Anyway, let's say these two together
反正就要說這兩個加起來
is what we get
就是我們要素所得
Anyway, besides sleeping
就反正除了睡之外
probably these two
大概這兩個
In addition to sleeping and the so-called depreciation
除了睡還有所謂的折舊之外
It's probably mainly these two.
大概主要就是這兩個就對了
hand
手的
You got these two
你手上拿到手的就是這兩個
not these two
不是這兩個
Let's say these two have a trend
我們說這兩個有一個趨勢
what trend
什麼趨勢
You see this social staff pay
你看到這個社會人員報酬
Around the time of the 19th year
大概在19幾年的時候
1989 reached a petition
1989年達到一個告訪
But then you see the whole trend and go down
但後來你看整個趨勢就往下走
what does this mean
這個表示什麼意思
This means that
這個表示就是說
economic growth
經濟成長當中
For example, economic growth
譬如說經濟成長
we are growing
我們在成長當中
belonging to labor income
屬於勞動所得
part of salary
薪資所得的部分
it is getting less and less
它是越來越少
Fewer and fewer
越來越少
in other words
換句話說
For example, it is equivalent to earning 100 yuan
譬如說等於是所得100塊
for 100 pieces
對 100塊
you see at this time
你看在這個時候
it takes half
它占到一半
right
對
about 50
大概50幾
accounted for half
占到一半
right
對
but then what
但是後來呢
a coat is falling
一個外套就在下跌
On the other hand, this is rising
反觀這個在上升
This phenomenon is not unique to Taiwan.
這個現象也不是台灣獨有的現象
phenomenon in many countries
很多國家都有的現象
So I saw this case earlier
所以前面看到這個case
Seeing equals the rising gap is getting bigger and bigger
看到等於是在上升差距越來越大
about is to say
關於就是說
For example, economic growth
譬如說經濟成長
say 3%
比如說3%
or 5%
或5%
Many people say that the five senses
很多人都說五感
because of the money
因為那些錢
My salary didn't increase either
我的薪水也沒有增加
Where will those 5% and 3% growth go?
那些5%、3%的成長跑去哪邊
In other words not universally enjoyed
換句話說不是普遍的享有
You can see that the early days of Taiwan were not like this
你現在看台灣的早期不是這個樣子
Early Taiwan
台灣早期
In the early stage of Taiwan, there were many opportunities at that time
台灣早期的話那個時候機會非常多
Almost I'm as small as among my peers
幾乎我小的像我的同伯當中
as long as high school
只要高中畢業
don't even go to college
甚至不便念大學
At that time everyone earned college
那一陣子大家都賺大學
At that time there were many chances
那時候機率很多
as long as you work hard
只要你認真努力
not that kind
不是那種
Let's just say how it is
我們就說很怎麼樣
In other words you just
換句話你只要
about that time
大概那時候的
equal to many chances
等於機率很多
everyone earns college
大家都賺大學
good
好
we learned to read very high
我們學會念得很高的
Doesn't necessarily make more money
不見得賺的錢比較多
But then we heard
但是那時候我們又聽到
What fat cat is not a fat cat question
什麼肥貓不肥貓的問題
But now you can come back to the whole standstill
但現在你可以回來到整個停滯下來
there is this phenomenon
就有這個現象
This phenomenon is tantamount to saying that
這個現象等於是有點就是說
I didn't earn the money
錢不是我賺到的
he made money
是他有錢的賺到
This phenomenon is also
這個現象也是
We see these two phenomena
我們看到這兩個現象
actually a
實際上是一個
But it's right that Taiwan has its own problems.
可是台灣獨有問題就對了
Don't talk about unique problems
不談獨有問題
why is it like this
為什麼是這樣
As you can imagine there are of course many factors behind this
你可以想像這個背後當然有很多因素
But probably globalization is probably
不過大概全球化大概是
presumably a factor of a running jump
大概是一個跑步跳的一個因素
globalization
全球化
Because labor is more expensive in your place
因為你這個地方人工比較貴
I won't set up a factory in your place
我就不在你這個地方設廠
I went to other places to set up factories
我就跑到其他地方設廠
But there are many factors behind
不過背後因素很多
But there is this phenomenon
不過就是有這個現象
How to overcome this phenomenon
這個現象怎麼克服
How to deal with it
怎麼解決
This is also a pretty big problem
這也是一個蠻大的一個問題
pretty big problem
蠻大的問題
Yes, and I want to make a special point about the previous one
對,然後我前面這個我要特別講一點
That is to say, among the income of the Taiwan government
就是說現在台灣政府的收入當中
Taiwan's government revenue is about 2 trillion a year
台灣的政府收入大概是一年大概兩兆多
2 trillion, other than 2 trillion including taxes
兩兆,就其他包括稅收等等兩兆
Ladies and gentlemen, what is the contribution of the central bank among the two trillion?
各位小不小的,兩兆當中中央銀行的貢獻是多少
You may never have thought that contributing is tithe
各位可能從來沒有想到貢獻是十分之一
In other words, two balls are the central bank's surplus
換句話說有兩球役是央行的盈餘
So if you think about it, we generally imagine that the central bank is the monetary policy
所以你想想看,央行我們一般的想像中央行是貨幣政策
It is to control the exchange rate interest rate those policies
它是要控制匯率利率那些政策
But the central bank has now become a tax unit that seems to be quite important
但央行現在變成一個好像是蠻重要的一個稅收單位
This is the unit that collects money
收錢的單位就是這個
Because out of a hundred dollars, out of a hundred dollars spent by the entire government
因為一百塊當中,整個政府的花費一百塊當中
Ten out of one hundred yuan of income is from the central bank
收入當中一百塊當中有十塊是央行的
200 billion is the contribution of the central bank
兩千億是央行的貢獻
If you think about it, this one is very special
你想想看,這個是非常特殊
It is a very special phenomenon in the world
在全世界上是非常特殊現象
But Yang Yangyang said, he would say
但楊洋洋說,他會說
I have a lot of foreign exchange reserves, and my base is very good
外匯存底很多,我基礁很不錯
But from the point of view of monetary scholars
但是就貨幣學者來看
that is also a tax
那個也是一種稅
Why?
為什麼?
If Yang Yangyang wants to make that money
楊洋洋要賺那個錢的話
He is bound to drive down interest rates
他勢必要把利率壓低
This is like a dispute
這個等於是有爭論啦
there is an argument
有爭論啦
But look, this is not a long-term occasion
但你看看,這個不是一個長久之際
You see, Yang Yangyang contributed one of ten papers, 200 billion
你看,楊洋洋貢獻十文之一,兩千億
Among the two trillion, two hundred billion is Yang Xing
兩兆當中,兩千億是楊行
this is very special
這個是非常特殊
This can't be long
這個絕對不可能是長久
So if you take away Yang Yangyang's share
所以你把楊洋洋那一份拿掉的話
that deficit is worse
那個赤字更嚴重
As I just said, the annual deficit is about 200 billion to 300 billion
我剛剛講過,每年赤字大概是兩千億到三千億
If you take Yang Yangyang away
把楊洋洋拿掉的話
Probably suddenly increased to 400 billion, 500 billion
大概就一下子暴增到四千億、五千億去了
And this is really, I think it's a pretty serious problem.
而這個實在是,我覺得是一個蠻嚴重的問題
Because Yang Yangyang has such a big burden
因為楊洋洋負擔那麼大的一個
you can tell
你可以看得出
I guess and intuit it too
我猜想 用直覺也想到
That is to say, he may interfere with one of his monetary policies
就是說他可能就會干擾他的一個貨幣政策
yes, should have, for example should have done
對 本來應該 譬如說應該這樣做
But considering that if you do this, it won't work out.
但是考慮到說 這樣做的話搞不好
I have less money or something
我這個錢就比較少或什麼樣
he will be restricted
他就會受到限制
So this is not a long time
所以這個也不是長久之際
But I want POINOUT to point it out
不過我要POINOUT的 要指出來就是說
The number of times in Taiwan is quite serious.
這個台灣的次數是蠻嚴重的
Because the central bank contributed 200 billion
因為央行貢獻到2000億
If you remove the part of the central bank
你把央行那一部分再拿掉的話
The number of times per year is 4
每年就次數就是4
Equal to this difference becomes
等於這差額就變成
Not 200 billion, hundreds of billions
不是2000億 上千億
Become 2000 equal to 400 billion to 500 billion
變成2000 等於4000億到5000億
so it looks serious
所以看起來是蠻嚴重的
serious
嚴重
Well by this I mean a simple one
那麼這個我指的一個簡單的一個
Of course there is a feeling
當然有個感覺
that feeling means
那個感覺就是說
For example, we follow
譬如說我們依照
One that produces a compilation of different faculties
產生不同系的編制的一個
The finances of our Republic of China
我們中華民國的財政
look at it
你看看它
Probably tax accounted for more than 73.0
大概稅收佔到73.0多
india also india
印度也印度
it's serious
是蠻嚴重的
I just said it's past twelve o'clock
我剛剛講這十二點多呢
The central bank contributes 10%
央行就貢獻了10%
Contribute 10%
貢獻10%
It means that the central bank is the most profitable state-owned institution
等於是央行是最賺錢的國營事業單位
it's really special
這實在是很特殊
maybe i thought maybe in
可能我才想可能在
It's also a surprise that I'm knowing
這也是很意外我在曉得的
Surprised to know
很意外在曉得
It's hard for ordinary people to imagine
這個一般人很難想像說
The central bank turned out to be the most profitable business unit
央行竟然是最賺錢的營運事業單位
But the damage that this says is that
不過這說的破壞就是說
A tax on locks is probably in favor
鎖的稅大概是贊成
Business tax praise so much
營運稅贊這麼多
These 30 years add up to about half
這三十歲大概加起來大概是一半
But what I just said at the beginning is to say
不過我剛剛講一開始就講就是說
The destruction I'm going to talk about today is the tax on locks
我今天要講的破壞就是鎖的稅
not as good as we thought
沒有我們想像那麼好
let's take a look
我們來看一下
The tax of the lock is theoretically an ideal tax word
鎖的稅在理論上它是一個滿理想的稅字
Why is it an ideal tax word?
為什麼是理想的稅字呢
because it can vary depending on the taxpayer's situation
因為它可以根據納稅人不同的情境
deliberately different persuasion
刻意不同的說服
For example, your home
比如說你家
do you have children
有沒有小孩
Is there a major disaster every year
每今年是不是有一個重大的災難
So or any sick medical expenses
所以或是有什麼生病醫療費用
particularly high
特別高
We have a so-called special deduction
我們就有一個所謂的特別扣除
Not a special deduction
也不是特別扣除
You can deduct it immediately
你可以立即扣除就對了
Because it depends on your persuasion how many people to support
因為它根據你的說服養人數是多少
how is your condition
你這個人狀況怎麼樣
So it can move forward according to different people
所以它可以根據不同人的前進
I tax it differently
我給它課不同的稅
This tax is theoretically called a direct tax
這個稅在學理上就把它叫做直接稅
direct tax
直接稅
because according to your condition
因為根據你的狀況
I design my tax system
我來設計我的稅制
If there is a tax, we villains generally can't scold
一面稅的話我們小人一般是不能罵
For example, if you go to buy a
比如說你去買一個
For example, LV bags
比如說LV的包包
you like to buy
你很喜歡買
Buy LV bags from a rich man
跟一個有錢人買LV的包包
It won't say LV bags this guy is rich
它不會去說LV包包這個傢伙是有錢的
this guy has no money
這個傢伙是沒錢的
Maybe there is someone who likes LV bags very much
搞不好有一個很喜歡LV包包
it has no money
它沒什麼錢
but it also buys a
但它還買一個
so it can't see
所以它不能看
Anyway, it knows when it sees
反正它就看到就知道
Only one L88 was sold
就一個L88賣出去的
As for who bought it
至於是誰買的
he can't see
他是看不到
right
對
So what about general sales tax?
所以一般的營業稅呢
Generally, only the size of one car can be delivered
一般只能依交一輛的大小
That is to say, how much are you buying and selling
就是說你買賣量的多少
He is not able to adapt to the different circumstances of the taxpayer
他是不能依照納稅人的不同情境
I just said that it's like a tax breaker
像手隔稅的我剛剛講
I can see how many children you have
可以看見說你有幾個小孩
did you raise your parents
你有沒有撫養父母
Did you have any major events this year?
你今年有沒有重大的
For example, disaster
譬如說災害
Are you sick? etc.
有沒有生病等等
he can make an adjustment for you
他可以給你做一個調整
For example, when you enumerate deductions
譬如說你在列舉扣除的時候
You can list your medical expenses and so on.
你就可以把你的醫療會用列上去等等
So he can according to the situation of different people
所以他可以根據不同人的情境
different taxation
可以不同稅課
But sales tax is gone
但營業稅不行了
sales tax anyway
營業稅反正就是說
you trade
你買賣
The tax of the father who has money to buy you is the same
有錢來買你的父的稅都是一樣
all the same
都是一樣
So generally speaking
所以一般這樣的話
Different taxes cannot be levied according to different situations of taxpayers
不能依照納稅人不同情境課的不同稅
indirect tax
一般就叫間接稅
This is called Direct Tax
這個叫Direct Tax
words in english
用英文來說的話
This is called In Direct Tax
這個叫In Direct Tax
So theoretically
所以學理上
in theory
理論上
Hand tax is a better tax
手隔稅是一個比較好的稅
because it can advance according to different
因為它可以根據不同的前進
This measure of customer tax means that
這個量人客稅就是說
What we traditionally say is
我們傳統講的就是說
People with higher income should pay more tax
你所得高的人應該繳比較多的稅
Those who earn less should pay more
所得比較少的人應該比較繳
less tax etc.
比較少的稅等等
The person with the two heads going forward should pay the tax for the head and so on
兩個像頭前進的人應該繳像頭的稅等等
It can be done differently according to this forward
它可以根據這個不同前進做
Just a different design
不同的設計就對了
But sales tax is not
但營業稅不行
No business tax, that is to say
營業稅不行就是說
anyway each of you
反正你每個人
Yes, you go to a high-end restaurant to eat
對啊你去高級餐廳吃
You just have to pay five business taxes
你就是要繳五趴營業稅
It doesn't matter who eats it
誰吃他就不管了
You are buying Taiwanese people to eat, so it is the same
你是購台民去吃也是這樣
I also pay this tax when I eat today
我今天吃也是繳這個稅
yes
對啊
So in theory
所以理論上的話
Judgment from the point of view of taxation
量人客稅觀點來判定的話
The tax in my hand is the excellent business tax
我手的稅是優異營業稅
Merit business tax
優異營業稅
But what I'm going to say next is that
但我底下要說的就是說
The tax in hand is not as good as we imagined
手的稅有沒有我們想像中那麼好
let's take a look
我們來看看一下
the information i use
我用的資料
The information used below is from 1994
底下用的資料是94年的
China's hand tax approved production and trade information
中國手的稅的核定生貿資料
because my year happened to be
因為我那一年剛好
make one for the treasury
替財政部做一個
just make a plan
做一個計畫就對了
But now there is also, now there is a relatively new information
不過現在也有了,現在有個比較新的資料
But my understanding is not much different, let's take a look at the data of Zengnian
不過我的了解差別不大,我們就以增年的資料來看一下
Because the number of places reflected in the data, what is it?
因為資料上反應的處數,是什麼東西?
Let's take a look at the general guardian of the household
我們來看一下,當年的家戶總守者
Those who make friends mean, for example, husband and wife, if we come to see husband and wife
交手友者就是說譬如說夫妻,我們來夫妻來看的話
As long as your total number of defenders reaches 1.3 million, you can use the data of increasing years to see
你總守者只要到達130萬的話,用增年的資料來看
You are probably dead and rich in the first half of Taiwan
你大概就台灣前半是死的有錢
1.3 million, what is it like? Probably every month when you don’t expect to earn
130萬,大概是怎麼樣呢?大概每個月不期賺的時候
This does not include any deductions
這個還沒有包括扣掉什麼扣除有沒有
This gross is equivalent to not deducting anything, for example, how much you have raised children
這 gross 等於還沒有扣任何的譬如說你扶養小孩多少
You're going on vacation and haven't deducted those things yet.
你要放假還沒有扣掉那些東西
In other words, it is right to calculate that you have made money
單純的就是說,換算你有賺到手的就對了
You see, you only need to earn about 110,000
你看你只要手的大概賺到11萬
It's the 10% of rich people
就是屬於10%的有錢人
in other words
換句話說
as long as your husband and wife
只要你夫妻
If it is a public official
是公人員的話
If the husband and wife are both public servants
夫跟太太都是公人員的話
on the tax package
在包稅資料上
You're probably in the 10% rich
你大概就是10%的有錢人
in other words
換句話說
The couple's money for every other diamond
夫妻每隔一鑽的錢
As long as it exceeds 113,000 yuan
只要超過11萬3000元
About 10% of rich people
大概就屬於10%的有錢人
Think about it, everyone
各位想想
This is the rich man you imagine
這個跟你們想像的有錢人
I guess there is a gap
我猜想是有段差距的
Both husband and wife are public servants
夫妻都是公人員
probably rich
大概就是有錢人
when i come
我來的時候
Our rental laboratory also
我們那租金驗室還
tell me
告訴我
Probably your ancestor and wife
大概你先人跟太太
All the words handed over at the university
都在大學交出的話
You're probably in the top 5% of rich people.
你大概就是前5%的有錢人
out of 100 people
100個人當中
you're probably in fifth place
你大概就排第五名
No. 6 is right
第六名就對了
This is the rich man we imagined
這個跟我們想像當中的有錢人
there is a gap
是有段差距的
But it appears on the tax information
但包稅資料上呈現出來
that's the number
就是這個數
The member of the tax return information is you see you as long as each
報稅資料成員就是你看你只要每個
It's not your money, it's a couple's money
這不是你個人是夫妻賺的錢
As long as it exceeds 110,000, I don’t know if it’s not more than 100,000 in life
只要超過11萬我不曉得在做人是不是不超過
If it exceeds, you probably belong on the tax return.
要超過的話你大概就屬於在報稅資料上
10% of the rich
1%之10%的有錢的
10% of the 1% are rich
1%之10%有錢的
There is a gap between this and our common sense understanding.
這個跟我們就是我們一般常識的了解是有差距的
If your husband and wife together earn more than 110,000 a month
你每個月夫妻加起來賺11萬多的話
I think it's okay, it's okay
我想還好啦還好啦
But it shouldn't be 10% of the money, right?
但應該不是10%的錢了吧
Also let's look at
另外我們看一下
In our data about that year
我們大概那一年的資料當中
There are about 5.5 million total registered students
總生報戶大概有550萬戶
The total number of family members has not reached 600,000
家庭總守的沒有到達60萬
About 595,000
大概59.5萬的
About 72.35% of all registered households
占全部生報戶大概72.35
In other words
換言之呢
There are approximately 3 out of 40,000 registered households in Taiwan
台灣大概有將近4萬之3的生報戶
His monthly household income is less than 50,000 yuan
他每個月的家庭收入不到5萬塊
can you believe this number
你相不相信這個數字
Siwenwen is three families, among the 5.5 million households listed on the tax filing information,
四溫溫是三個家庭,在報稅資料上550萬戶當中,
Siwen is a family of three, and every couple earns less than 50,000 yuan.
四溫是三個家庭,每隔也夫妻賺的錢還不到5萬塊,
This is the tax return information, the presented information,
這是報稅資料,呈現的資料,
What does this mean? He will ask for a lot, and if he doesn’t have a lot of money, it’s like having a family with four Wen Wen,
這個表現什麼,他會求的很多,沒錢很多,等於是有四溫溫家庭,
I can't earn 50,000 yuan every time, neither the account nor too big,
每隔也賺不到5萬塊,不是賬戶也不是太大,
Every time the husband and wife add up, or the wife does not have a job,
每隔也夫妻加起來,或者是太太沒工作,
Anyway, it means that there are nearly 72.3, and I probably have four Wenwen families,
反正就是說有將近72.3,我大概將近四溫溫家庭,
It’s probably less than 50,000 yuan every time. In other words, what you see here is that,
每隔也大概賺不到5萬塊,換句話這裡看到的就是說,
What I saw in the tax returns is that the rich people in Taiwan are not so rich,
在報稅資料上看到的就是說,台灣的有錢人不是那麼有錢,
There are quite a lot of poor people in Taiwan, quite a lot,
台灣沒錢的人蠻多的,蠻多的,
This is in line with our common sense, our general understanding,
這個跟我們常識的認定,我們一般的了解,
Injury is a big gap
傷是滿大的差距的
And what we just saw was a
然後我們剛剛看到的是一個
tax filing information
報稅的資料
tax information
報稅資料
we want a
我們想一個
He has a household ratings survey
主義處他有一個家庭收視調查
He also investigates with each other as a unit
他也是以互為單位去調查
each other as a unit
互為單位去
The two surveyed households
這兩個調查的家戶
The definition sheet is different
定義單不一樣
It's the family rating of the doctrine department. He has a family unit.
就是主義處的家庭收視他有一個家戶單位
The first tax return has a household unit
首個稅申報有一個家戶單位
but if you think about it
但你想想看
Which household has more units
哪個家戶的單位會比較多
Because we know taxes are exhausting
因為我們曉得稅是累盡的
so he is exhausted
所以他是累盡的
so
所以
if you
假如你
If the child has money
小孩有賺錢的話
Of course you want him
你當然希望他
Do not declare together
不要一起申報
right
對
Taxes will be lower if you file separately
分開申報稅會比較低
Because if you add up your child
因為把你小孩被加起來的話
because taxes are exhausting
因為稅是累盡的
So the added tax rate would be
所以加起來的稅率會
The tax rate will be higher.
稅會稅率會比較高就對了
so you can imagine
所以你可以想像
From a tax point of view
從報稅觀點來看的話
a family, a family
一個家庭,一個家庭
He may separate the child to hold
他可能就會把小孩分出去抱
Yes, separate and hug
對,分出去抱
he won't drink him up and hug him
他不會把他喝起來抱
So in theory
所以理論上來看的話
Negative numbers on tax returns
報稅資料的負數
should be more than the family budget
應該會超過家庭收支
the negative number defined by
所定義的那個負數
because you are in the family budget
因為你在家庭收支
when doing research
在做調查的時候
In your family, for example
你一個家庭裡面譬如說
Your husband and wife have a child, and the child has a job
你夫妻有個小孩,小孩有工作了
he sees him as a
他就把他看成一副
but when filing taxes
但是在報稅的時候
That child may be separated from another life insurance
那個小孩他可能是分開另外生保
so in theory
所以理論上
in theory
理論上
that is
就是說
Your
你那個
Households subject to tax life insurance
所稅生保的家戶
It should be better than the life insurance of family income and expenditure
應該會比家庭收支的生保
more housework
家務來得多
but anyway
但不管怎麼樣
Among the data of the same year
同年的資料當中
About 7.1 million households reported household income and expenditure
家庭收支的報告大概有710萬戶
what we just said
我們剛剛講的
Taxable life insurance approximately 500
所稅生保大概有500
or Wanhu
或是萬戶
If there are tax shares, there are about 1.6 million households
如果有稅股的話大概有160萬戶
legal exchange
不管是合法匯法
no tax return at all
完全沒有報稅
We know that we were promoting
我們曉得當初在推行
Not when Ao was in health insurance
不是奧在健保的時候
There was an idea at the time that
當時有一個想法就是說
We're going to use virtual income to calculate health insurance premiums
我們要以虛擬所得計算健保費
I think they were probably scared at the time, that is
我想他們當時可能就怕了就是說
many people get nothing
很多人都沒所得
or did not report or something
或沒報或什麼東西
So I presume an income with you
所以我跟你推定一個所得
virtual income
他當時把叫虛擬所得
But Oboe's Picture
不過Oboe的Picture
The whole is to say from the data of 1994
整個就是說從94年的資料上來看的話
then it feels like
那麼感覺到就是說
Hey, talk about rich people
誒 談得有錢人
not so rich
沒那麼有錢
you only need income
你只要收入
As long as the monthly income is more than 110,000 points
每個月收入只要是11萬點多
Less than 120,000
還不到12萬
You are probably one of 100 people
你大概就是100個人當中
You'll be number 10
你就排第10名就對了
you probably said
你大概說
in other words
換句話說
you're good
你就很不錯就對了
This is what we imagined
這跟我們想像中
Couples add up every month
每個月夫妻加起來的
Earn 110,000
賺得所得11萬
This is not much, is it?
這個不是多吧
As long as your family is a civil servant
你家裡只要是公務人員
Both husband and wife are civil servants
夫妻都是公務人員
probably earn that much
大概就賺那麼多
Because we see that there are almost three-quarters of more than 72 points
因為我們看到就是將近有四分之三72點多
The family income is still less than 50,000 yuan per month
家庭收入還賺不到每個月 還賺不到5萬塊
And what about this place, we said
然後這個地方呢 我們又說
The household information reported should be larger than the negative household income information
報數的家戶資料應該比家庭收入的那個負數的資料來得大
Suppose we make it equal
假設我們讓它相等好了
You also see that there are probably very high negative numbers
你也看到大概有很那麼高的負數
No reporting at all, in other words, regardless of its legality
根本就沒有報 換句話說 不管它合法揮法
That is, it cannot be seen on the report data
就是它就在報數資料上就看不到
This idea, this idea locks the tax machine
這個想法 這個想法就鎖了稅機
It is to be full of seriousness, to erode the idea of ​​full seriousness
是要滿嚴重 侵蝕滿嚴重這個想法
In the following example, it is necessary to obtain a confirmation indirectly
在下面這個例子裡面是要間接的獲得一個證實
an indirect confirmation
間接獲一個證實
This is general science
這個是普通學呢
We know that before Ma Ying-jeou came to power in 2004
我們曉得在馬英九在2004年還沒上台之前
While he was running for his credentials, he had an idea
他在競選證件的時候 他有一個想法
This idea, maybe the student gave him a catch
這個想法 可能學生給他一個接獲
How about this idea? The idea is that they have a N income credit with the United States.
這個想法怎麼樣?這個想法就是跟美國有一個他們把叫N income credit
What is this? This means that you are serious about your work
這個什麼東西呢?這個就是說你很認真的工作
but your income is low
但是你所得在很低
For example, I go to sell McDonald's and work many hours every month.
比如說我每個月都去賣當勞工作很多小時
But the time to sell McDonald's is only 100 yuan
但賣當勞的時間只有100塊
No matter how much I earn, no matter how many hours I work
再賺的再多,我工作時間再多
The United States may also earn very low, and it is still very low now
美國也可能賺的還是很低,現在還是很低
What about this kind of person? The idea of ​​N income credit is this kind of person
對這種人怎麼樣呢?N income credit的想法就是這種人
I'll subsidize him
我這種就給他補貼
How to subsidize it? If you earn 100 yuan, I will subsidize you, for example, 20 yuan
怎麼補貼呢?你賺100塊的話我就補貼你譬如說20塊
In other words, your income becomes 120 yuan
換句話說你的收入就變成120塊
This is the so-called N income credit
這個就是所謂的N income credit
This plan has been around for a long time in the United States.
這個計畫在美國很早就有了
But the Kundin era greatly expanded it
但是Kundin時代就把它大大的擴充
what is the main idea of ​​this thing
這個東西主要的想法怎麼樣
The idea is that it doesn't just give you money
這個想法等於是它不是直接給你錢
On the contrary, it often has some regulations, that is,
反而就是說它往往有些規定就是說
You have to work faster than a certain speed
你必須要工作時速要超過某一個時速
For example, every other week to exceed an hour
譬如說每隔一個禮拜要超過一個時速
You can enjoy this benefit
你才能夠享受這個好處
So it is not quite the same as the concept of social welfare
所以它跟社會福利概念是不大一樣的
Social welfare concept is you don't have money
社會福利概念就是你沒有錢
shall i just give you the money
我就直接給你錢嗎
It is not
它不是
It's like saying you're serious about your work
它等於說你很認真的工作
but don't know why
但是不曉得什麼原因
you don't make much money
你就賺的錢就不多
so i subsidize you
所以我就補助你
This program is now in the US in Europe
這個方案現在在美國 在歐洲
are very popular
都是很流行的方案
Because this scheme is equivalent to
因為這個方案等於是
Just make you willing to work
讓你會願意工作就對了
This plan is equivalent to if you do not work
這個方案等於是你不工作的話
Instead of getting the money
反而領不到這個錢
you have to work
你要工作
And the working speed must exceed a certain standard
而且工作時速要超過某一個標準
You can get this money
你才能夠領到這個錢
This idea was developed when Miku was running for office in 2004
這個想法在滿久在2004年競選的時候
it brings up this thing
它就提出這個東西
It really did when it came on stage
它上台的時候也真的有做
these two
這兩座
what did you think
當時想法怎麼樣
It's called the Working Income Supplement for all.
這個全民叫做工作所得補助方案
This is generally called the Jianping scheme
這一般就把它稱為健平方案
His target is over 20 years old
他的對象是年滿20歲
did not reach the age of 65
沒有到達65歲
full primary earner
全副的主要收入者
For example, Mr. and Mrs.
比如說先生太太
His personal annual salary is below 300,000
他個人年薪在30萬以下
full time worker
全職工作者
So you see he has a rule that says
所以你看他有個規定就是說
your annual salary is lower
你年薪要低
but full time
但是要全職
In other words, you didn't mean guess what?
換句話說你不是說監猜怎麼樣
It means that you are really doing work.
等於是你真的有在做工作就對了
The working hours are still high
工作時數還滿高的
But the money you earn is very low
但是你就賺的錢就很低了
i will help you
我就來補助你
How did you do it?
當時做法是怎麼做法呢
At that time the practice was
當時做法就是
Because he is a social welfare bearer
因為他是一個社會福利涵納
So the Ministry of the Interior is in charge
所以是由內政部在負責
How does the Ministry of the Interior use it?
內政部他怎麼用去做呢
He took the taxation center of the Ministry of Finance as the
他就以財政部的財稅中心的
Based on fiscal and tax data from 1990
90年財稅的資料為基礎
compare
進行比對
able to screen out qualified candidates
能夠篩選出合格者
And then through the county and city governments
再透過各縣市政府
Active Program Application
主動計劃申請
to those who qualify
給符合資格者
in other words
換句話說
It uses this tax information
它是利用這個財稅資料
you go to filter
你們去篩選
Assuming you are a full child worker
就你假如是全子工作者
then your personal salary
那你個人的薪水
this means
這個就是說
your main paycheck
你主要的薪水者
Personal annual salary is low
個人年薪又偏低
For example, less than 300,000
比如30萬以下
I'm like
我就等於是
Active Planning Fact Sheet for you
主動的計畫通識單給你
I'm getting ready now
就我現在正準備
take this NNK
採取這個NNK
of the money you make
你賺的錢當中
My government will subsidize you some money
我政府就補貼你一些錢
the idea
這個想法
we found a big problem
我們就發覺到很大的問題
this problem
這個問題
we would like
我們想
this policy
這個政策
not that you apply
不是說你來申請
No
沒有
It is to filter from fiscal and taxation data
它是從財稅資料中去篩選
then look at you
然後看你
not enough hands
手都不夠
I will take the initiative to inform you that
我就主動的通知你說
You are eligible to receive this money
你有這個資格來領這個錢
so not
所以不是
in other words
換句話說
You don't even need to apply.
你自己都不用申請就對了
It informs about proactive programs
它就主動計畫通知
just for you
單給你
So the government took the initiative
所以政府主動出擊
Probably the biggest feature of this contraband plan
大概是這個禁品方案的最大特色
not you to apply
不是你來申請
then go up to filter
然後上去篩選
But the place is out of the game
但是地方就主動出局
Probably not as good as the so-called Chinese
大概也不如說中國所謂的
Therefore, the application materials have an authenticity
所以申報資料有一個施真性
There is a problem with this information
這個資料上很有問題
For example, the China Times on October 3, 1997
譬如說97年10月3日的中國時報
it has a report
它就有個報導
This program appears as the subsidy object for the factory director
該方案出現工廠負責人補助對象
Quite a lot
蠻多的
because you look
因為你看看
If you go to subsidize
你去補助的話
Maybe through the Lichang or something to get to know him
可能透過里長還是什麼去通識他
you have the qualifications
你有這個資格領
The consular district on the left is small
左一個領區就小的
The consular district on the left is of course small
左一個領區當然小的
is this guy rich
這個家伙是不是有錢多少
Is it rich to get this?
領這個是不是有錢
probably small
大概就小的
So you go and see
所以當時你們去看一下
local newspaper at the time
當時的地方報紙
In many places, the prophecy is directly elected
很多的地方預言就直選
why
為什麼呢
why he can get
為什麼他可以領
i can't take it
我就不能領
this problem happens
就發生這個問題
I have no money than him
我比他沒錢
why he can get
為什麼他能夠領
i can't take it
我就不能領
so at that time
所以當時
local and central
地方還有中央
For example, the Southern Legislative Council at that time
譬如說當時的南立立委
just throw the Ministry of the Interior
就一次拋內政部
Disbursed on the practice of subsidizing Hunan
就補助湖南做法出帳
How about that's the Ministry of the Interior?
那是內政部的懷打怎麼樣
that's computer choice
那是電腦選擇
I'm a changing profile
我是更衣資料啊
I'm choosing
我在選啊
So what about this plan?
所以這個方案呢
It's like being exposed
等於是就暴露出來
This code tax is actually full of problems
這個守則稅實上是滿有問題的
It reflects only one of the Chinese code tax data
它反映的只是中國守則稅資料的一個
I especially wanted to study the Jianmin plan at that time.
建民方案我還特別當時要研究這個
I also went to the Ministry of the Interior to ask him for advice.
我還特別去內政部去跟他請教
Do you have any information
說你們有沒有資料
Then how can I refer to
那我可以參考怎麼樣
What about the Ministry of the Interior?
上內政部呢
He deleted all the information about the Jianmin plan
他把所有的建民方案的資訊全部刪掉
as if this never happened
好像從來沒有發生過這件事情一樣
Because this seems to be a very embarrassing thing
因為這個是好像是很糗的一件事情
yes embarrassing thing
對 很糗的一件事情
It's not a benefit
不是一個福利就對了
My plan is
我這個方案就是
So all the information about the Jianmin project
所以所有的有關建民方案的訊息
you are online now
你在現在網上上就
as if this never happened
好像這件事情從來沒有發生過
never happened
從來沒有發生過
But what I'm saying is
不過我要說的就是說
Let's see from the data
我們前面從資料上去看
90 years of information to see
90年資料去看
we have strong doubts
我們有強烈的懷疑
This Solo tax deep insurance is quite substantial
這個索羅稅深保是蠻實質的
You only need to earn more than 110,000 points every month
你只要每個月賺了11萬點多
Less than 120,000
還不到12萬
You're probably in the 10% rich
你大概就是10%的有錢人
The rich man we imagine is for you to check
這個我們想像的有錢人是讓你去查
In other words, your husband and wife are probably not too bad.
換句話說 你家夫妻大概是一般不太差的
For example, workers
譬如工人員
you don't want to be superior
你不要做到什麼上級的
It's probably up to that standard.
大概就可以達到那個標準就對了
Then additionally we see
然後另外我們看到
Less than 50,000 yuan
不到5萬塊的
A bunch of people didn't reach 50,000 yuan
一堆人都沒有到達5萬塊
Nearly three quarters more than 72 points
將近四分之三72點多
The monthly salary is less than 50,000 yuan
每個月賺的薪水還不到5萬塊
In addition, we report
另外我們在申報資料上
Comparing the data of the doctrine number with the tax declaration data
用主義數的資料跟報稅資料來比的話
we have reason to believe
我們有理由相信
There are probably more than 1.6 million households
大概有超過160萬戶人
Probably the tax system has not grasped it at all
大概稅制完全沒有掌握到
It's legal and illegal, it's fine if you don't declare it
它是合法非法 它沒有申報就對了
the concept in this
這個概念在這個
not on the plan
就不方案上
I feel like getting a confirmation
我覺得多少獲得一個證實
Because the characteristic of this program is that
因為這個方案的特色就是說
you don't have to apply
你不必來申請
I use the data
我用資料上
Maybe the Ministry of the Interior didn't even think of saying
可能當時內政部也沒有想到說
have this problem
有這個問題
Because how he repays is to let you go to Hong Kong
因為他怎麼報紓是要讓你香港
This compensation is for his authenticity
這個報紓是要有他的真實性的話
he won't have this problem
他就不會有這個問題發生
Because if you have no money, you really have no money.
因為沒錢的就真的沒錢嘛
But Hua Xuedao said the subsidy object
但是花學道就說補助對象
may not be right
可能都不對
Because the left and right fields are small
因為左右領域小了
this guy is rich
這個家伙滿有錢的
he drives the car
他開著車子
You can probably tell that he lives in a house.
他住了房子大概就可以看得出來
why he can get
為什麼他能夠領
i can't take it
我就不能領
So if you check the newspapers at that time
就造成假如你們去查當時的報紙
Many local councils have a consultation
地方很多議會都有一個咨詢
because it's going to spread
因為這個事情會傳開來
This guy can take
這個家伙能夠領
I guess he's probably going to be gone.
我猜想他可能都會離長了
to distribute
去發放
Maybe the left and right fields are small
可能左右領域就小的
say this can take
說這個能夠領
why can't i get it
我為什麼不能領
Even if it's a big problem
就算滿大的問題
But the whole old man
不過整體老人
i hope i mean
我是希望就是說
There is a Matchity
有一個Matchity
This Matchity means
這個Matchity就是說
Shou Luo Tax Division
守羅稅課
More imaginary Shouluo tax
更想像中的守羅稅
That's right
差很大就對了
Obviously there are a lot of designs in Taiwan's income
很顯然台灣所得當中有很多的設計
did not grasp at all
根本就沒有掌握到
Like I said we can get hold of now
像我說我們現在能夠掌握到的
Most everything has buckle corners and flat sheets
最什麼都是有扣角平單的
Flat single with buckle angle
有扣角平單的
In other words, if you're filing your taxes, you're underage.
換句話說你在報稅的話你就小了
If you are required to file taxes
報稅是要你上去的話
All your information is meat
你的資料全部當肉
All those things are produced and all of them are mastered
那個東西都產生部有掌握到
what is that
那個都是什麼東西
It's like your salary
都是譬如說你的薪水
For example, the company sends you encouragement
比如公司發放你的鼓勵
or what bank pays your interest
或者是什麼銀行發放你的利息
Those are all SER parties
那個都是有SER Party
The bank will pay you a salary
銀行要發給你薪息的
when the interest
那個利息的時候
He will take the initiative to notify
他就會主動通知
the irs says
國稅局說
How much interest do I give him?
我這個人給他多少的利息
or when the company wants to pay dividends
或公司要發放紅利的時候
He will take the initiative to notify
他就會主動的通知
the irs says
國稅局說
how much encouragement does this guy get
這個傢伙領到多少的鼓勵
This is all with SER Party
這個都是有SER Party
Once there is a SER Party
一旦有SER Party的話
you probably won't be able to escape
你大概就不可能逃了
Because it is equal to the national tax unit
因為等於是國稅單位就
fully grasped
充分掌握住了
But now the problem is no Street Party
但現在問題就沒有Street Party的
Taiwan can't do it well
台灣搞不好
Because of Taiwan when we were young
因為台灣我們小時候
Taiwan has a characteristic
台灣有個特色
Middle-aged and old enterprises are particularly developed
中老企業特別發達
So I think the question
所以我覺得這個問題
It's not about the water
不是怪水的問題
because i think it's
因為我覺得這是
structural problems
結構性的問題
it has two structural problems
它有兩個結構性的問題
like i said
就像我說了
One problem, of course, is that our middle-aged and old enterprises
一個問題當然是我們中老企業
It's us Tang Da
是我們唐大
These are all year round
這些是滿年活的
Live all year round
滿年活的
i used to say
我曾經就是說
I am a student
我一個學生
He is the person expected at the beginning of the year
他是歲先期望的人員
he once told me
他曾經告訴我
It's really useless to catch them.
其實抓到這些也沒什麼大用
useless
沒有大用
He might just declare bankruptcy or something
他可能就是宣布倒閉或什麼東西
And here is a profile
而且這裡有個資料
This data also tells us that
這個資料也告訴我們說
this is really not easy
這個真的是不容易
Because the statistics of the United States
因為美國的統計資料
He says it's not easy to be a solo business
他說非容易的獨自企業
This is the so-called sale improvement
這個就是一般所謂的sale improvement
It's like being your own boss.
等於自己當老闆就對了
look
你看
His data is about 57%
他的資料大概有57%
will be exposed
會被淘露掉
In other words, for moviegoing friends
換句話說,對於收影朋友們
not one from taiwan
不是台灣的一個說
it's hard for you to grasp
你很難掌握到
The United States has based on their data
美國都有根據他們資料
estimated
估算出來
It's like researching it
等於是研究出來
About half of the income
大概一半以上的收的
Like one hundred yuan, about fifty-seven
像一百塊當中,大概五十七塊
you probably didn't get it
你大概沒有掌握到
so this is a
所以這是一個
tantamount to a real problem
等於是一個現實的問題
real problem
現實的問題
You can't shoot that every day
你不可能天天拍那個
So everyone gives him every day
所以人人天天給他
praise him
給他讚綱
And the atmosphere is really a lot
而且氣氛真的是很多
In fact, if you go out of Taiwan now
其實你現在台灣出去的話
everyone is doing business
每個都在做生意
angry so much
氣那麼多
You can't make every family smaller
你不可能每一家都小了
some more famous
有些比較有名
For example, when I was young, didn’t I have Fuhang Soymilk?
比如說我小時候不是有一個富航豆漿
Fuhang soy milk is famous
富航豆漿滿有名的
When I was young, this family was full of famous
小時候,這一家滿有名的
villain is good
小人不錯
Of course he will give you the account
他就當然就給你賬綱
he can see
他就可以看
look , you sold so much
你看,你賣了那麼多
You paid taxes so why so little
你繳了稅又什麼那麼少
he has reason
他就有理由
but that is to say
但是就是說
So he's like those too famous
所以他就等於是那些太有名的
probably not so good
可能也不是那麼好
Because the national tax is of course small
因為國稅當然就小的
Your business is very good
你這家生意很不錯
outside of those
那些之外
Check each one for you
每一家都給你查吧
So this is a problem, Taiwan comes out
所以這是一個問題,台灣出來
So if in the process of enterprise development
所以假如在企業發展過程當中
For example, getting bigger and bigger, for example, look at
比如說越來越大,譬如說你看看
There used to be a lot of grocery stores in Taiwan
台灣過去很多的雜貨店
That tax may be difficult to control
那個稅大概就很難掌握住
But when you become 711, it's different
但你後來變成711,那就不一樣
In the case of 711, the national tax unit will fully grasp
711的話,國稅單位就充分掌握住
Because in the case of 711, it unifies itself and needs to control it internally
因為711的話,它統一自己都內部要控制
In terms of internal control, it must have a document so that false reports cannot be made
內部控制的話,它就必須要有一個資料就不能報假
Therefore, throughout the development process, if
所以在整個發展過程當中,假如說
Change to 711 for grocery stores
就雜貨店變成711
We know that this kind of tax will increase
我們就曉得,這種的稅收就會增加
Because the grocery store is difficult to control, 711 probably controls the tax
因為雜貨店很難掌握住,711大概稅收就掌握住
Taiwan has such a problem
台灣有這麼一個問題
In addition, I think there is a problem that
另外我覺得有一個問題就是說
Taiwan is an open and small economy
台灣是一個開放的小型經濟
locks out easily
鎖得很容易流出去
All I talk about is that I don't know
我最談的只是說,我不曉得
Can this be used as an indicator?
這個可不可以當作一個觀察指標
For example, the United News Network has a reward
比如說這個聯合新聞網它有一個報答
Commonwealth Magazine joined an international consortium of investigative journalists in July 2003
天下雜誌在2003年7月加入一個國際調查記者聯盟
Aiming at the status of overseas offshore assets in the Dazhong area
針對大眾網地區境外離岸資產狀況
A six-month investigation
展開長達半年的調查
According to this decrypted data
根據這個解密資料的話
Overseas offshore asset holders in the Dazhong area probably
大眾網地區的境外離岸資產持有者大概
Accounted for 35% of all data
佔全體資料35
Among them Taiwan
其中台灣
about this many
大概有這麼多的
1.5 times that of Hong Kong
是香港的1.5倍
China's 1.5
中國的1.5
The Union of Journalists
該記者聯盟
Taiwanese use tax shelter computers far more than Hong Kong
台灣人使用的避稅電腦程度遠勝香港
Repay here
這邊報答
but maybe
但是可能
There are different
有不同的
an interpretation
一個解讀
not as good as you can imagine
不如你可以想像得到
Because many people in Taiwan do business outside
因為台灣很多在外面做生意
I understand that many of them just set up an account overseas.
我了解就是他們很多就是在海外大概就設一個帳戶
this account
這個帳戶
so
所以
Taiwan to tax the rich
台灣要對有錢人課稅
not as easy as we imagined
不是我們想像那麼容易
From the point of view of education
從學歷上來看
talk about what you get
講你所得
very quickly
很迅速的
From an efficiency point of view
從效率觀點來看
It should have been lower tax rate
它本來稅率就要比較低一點
because you can imagine
因為你可以想像到
A piece of land is over there
一塊土地的話擺在那邊
how do you give it the gram
你怎麼給它克
it's the land
它就那塊土地
The tax should be higher
這個稅就應該高一點
on the other hand
反過來說
it equals in and out quickly
它等於進出很快
you give it a little boost
你給它稍微提高一點
it just ran away
它就跑掉了
tax loss
稅收就損失
Very serious
很嚴重
such tax
這樣的稅
Tax rates should have been lower
稅率本來就應該低一點
From the point of view of education
從學歷上來看
Taiwan is an open economy again
台灣又是開放經濟
Then Taiwan has another problem
然後台灣有另外一個問題
That is to say, it does not have diplomatic relations with many countries.
就是說跟很多國家都沒有邦交
no diplomatic relations at all
根本就沒有邦交
Sometimes we can pass an equal to
有的時候我們可以透過一個等於是
an exchange of information
資訊的一個交換
information exchange
資訊交換
For example, in the tax department
比如說財稅單位當中
exchange of information
資訊的交換
can be mastered
可以掌握到
For example, between you and the mainland
比如說你跟大陸之間
pay an information exchange
繳一個資訊交換的話
I know the money you make in mainland China
你在大陸賺的錢我就曉得了
You, a Taiwanese businessman, made money in mainland China
你這個台商在大陸賺的錢
I know how much money I make
我就曉得賺多少錢
But Taiwan has a problem
但台灣有一個問題
That is to say, it has no political relations with many countries.
就是說跟很多國家都沒有政治的邦交
so at this point
所以在這一點上
It's not so easy now
現在上就比較不那麼容易
have faced a difficulty
有面對一個困難
So it is not so easy for rich people in Taiwan
所以台灣有錢人事上不是那麼容易
then we have a discussion this afternoon
那我們今天下午有個討論
It's Zhu Qingying's luck
就是朱清英運事
He's been in therapy for financial problems lately
他最近在用財政問題治療
he's going to do a study
他要做一個研究
what is this research
這個研究是什麼東西
That is to say, the top one percent
就是說最高所得百分之一的人
For example, out of 100 people
比如說100個人當中
You are one of the highest version of people
你是最高版之一的人
he earns
他賺得所得
that is
就是說
How much of the 100 yuan is the top one percent of the income
100塊當中有多少是有最高所得百分之一的人
For example, earning materials is about 13 yuan
比如說賺到資料大概13塊多
In other words, among the 100 yuan
換句話說100塊當中
It is equal to the 100 yuan of our whole society
等於是我們整個社會100塊當中
The top one percent is about 13 yuan
最高百分之一的人大概13塊多
For example, on the data
譬如說資料上
I don't know the details, he remembers
詳細狀況我不知道他記得
But there is an interesting phenomenon
但是有一個有趣現象
let's draw
我們就畫一下
2012 words
2012年的話
because in 2008 words
因為在2008年的話
We know the financial tsunami
我們曉得金融海嘯
During the financial tsunami, the top one percent
金融海嘯的時候最高百分之一的人
you can draw
你可以畫一下
So we know that when the financial tsunami
所以我們曉得金融海嘯的時候
there is a decision
就有一個下定
He originally said that among the 100 yuan
他原先譬如說100塊當中
up to 13 percent
最高百分之13塊
In that year, you may only earn 7 yuan or 8 yuan
那一年就可能只賺到7塊8塊
so
這樣
In addition, we just made an interesting declaration
另外我們剛才有趣宣言一下
In 2012, we are ashamed
2012年的話我們不好意思
This proportion is also falling
這個比重也在下跌
then let's find out
那我們去瞭解一下
What happened in 2012
這個2012年究竟發生什麼事情
We know that happened to be the secretary of the treasury at the time
我們曉得剛好是那時候的財政部長
Who is that called?
那個叫誰啊
I've been going there also with the female treasury secretary
我一直往那裡也跟女的財政部長
Isn't he going to engrave the forehand tax?
他不是要刻正手稅嗎
carve a forehand tax
刻一個正手稅
You see, that year also made his proportion drop.
你看那一年也讓他比重在下跌
equal to
等於是
That is to say, to boil the eyes in the mouth, I think it means to say
就是說嘴裡熬眼我覺得就是說
Taiwanese want to tax the rich
台灣人要對有錢人課稅
not so easy
不是那麼容易的
they have a way
他們有的是辦法
there are ways
有的是辦法
It's like if you want to tax him
等於你要給他課稅的話
he ran to show you
他就跑給你看
So instead of a feature dispute
所以不是說功能爭議
This is the responsibility of making money
這就是錢賺的責
He should pay more tax
就應該讓他繳比較多的稅
From a business point of view
從事務觀點上來講
It's not that easy to see
來看的話沒那麼容易
So I think it's two structural
所以我覺得這是兩個結構上的
kind of question
類個問題
The first is greed for small and medium-sized enterprises
第一個就是貪中小企業
Tedo
特多
Everyone is their own boss
每個人都是自己當老闆
did you notice
你有沒有發覺到
your relatives and friends
你左右的親戚朋友
As long as it is a small and medium-sized enterprise
只要是做中小企業的話
Generally speaking
一般說來講
don't do too badly
不要做得太差
His life is probably more humorous than yours
他生活大概都比你幽默
but when it comes to paying taxes
但談到繳稅的話
You guarantee that he pays less tax than you
你保證他繳的稅一定比你少
compare your life to words
你的生活比較上的話
for example
譬如說
his house is better than yours
他的房子比你好
eat better than you
吃的也比你好
anything is better than you
什麼都比你好
But you have to actually ask him how much he pays in taxes
但你要真正問他繳多少稅
look
你看
You pay the new leader
你繳的是新之首的人
have you ever thought about
你有沒有想過
I guess they are higher
我猜想都比較高
not high
不是高
and much taller
而且高很多
So I think it's one of those in Taiwan
所以我覺得這是台灣上的一個
tantamount to a structural problem
等於是一個結構上的問題
the one we just talked about
我們剛剛講的一個
american words
美國的話
in fact internationally
實際上在國際上
There are 100 of them
有100塊當中
57 run away
57塊跑掉
So express this thing
所以表示這個東西
Actually it is not easy to grow
實際上是不容易長
has its difficulty
有它的困難度
For example, unless you invest a lot of resources
比如說除非你投下很多的資源就對了
If you invest a lot of resources
你投下很多資源的話
Say you receive a dollar
比如說你收到一塊錢
You have to pay fifty cents to collect
你要花到五毛錢去徵收
It's not worth it
搞不好也不划算
So there is a structural problem
所以有一個結構性上的問題
in other words
換句話說
There are many such series
這種系列特多
In addition, Taiwan is open to Qingjing
另外台灣是開放清境
Code is easy to flow out
守則很容易流出去
You have to tax some people
你要對有些人客稅
won't make it easy for you
不會讓你容易
so overall
所以整體而言
I think code tax
我覺得守則稅
It might not be as good as we imagined.
可能沒有我們想像中那麼好就對了
This is my main message
這是我主要的message
Code tax strictly speaking
守則稅嚴格上來講
It is a
它是一個
In theory a nice tax system
理論上是一個不錯的稅制
because it can be tailored to your individual situation
因為它能夠針對你的個人的狀況
Make a design for you to measure the customer tax
給你做一個設計量人客稅
But in practice
但實務操作上的話
I think at least in Taiwan
我覺得至少在台灣
Let's look at the data
我們從資料上來看
have a big problem
有很大的問題
It's quite different from what we imagined.
跟我們想像中的差距蠻大的
i think this
我覺得這個
Not that it's a problem I don't work on
不是說這我不努力的一個問題
it's a structural problem
這是結構性的問題
structural
結構性
If this is the case, we may have to think differently about the design of broken characters, and get out of the situation
假如是這樣的話,我們在碎字設計上可能要另媲想法,另媲脫境
It cannot be said that we will only strengthen the reform of broken gloves.
不能說我們就加強什麼手套碎的改革什麼樣
may have a different idea
可能要有另外不同的想法
So the underlying idea is that we know how to break into pieces
那麼底下想法就是說我們曉得拆成碎
Probably a space that can be considered
大概是一個可以考虑的一個空間
Let's take a look at this, of course everyone knows it
我們看一下這個當然是大家都曉得了
That newspaper is very big
那個報紙報的很大
That is to say, global housing prices are affordable
就是說全球的房價負擔的
Since Taipei City is higher than Hong Kong
台北市既然比香港都還高
It is the house price glove ratio
它是房價手套比
That is to say, the price of the gloves you earn is compared with your gloves
就是說你那個賺的手套房價跟你手套比
also more than several times
也是超過幾倍
more than several times
超過幾倍
You see us ordinary people in London, Los Angeles
你看我們一般人倫敦、洛杉磯
These are famous cities anyway
這些反正都是有名的城市
we are now taller than that
我們現在是比它還高
It's really hard to imagine a thing
這實在是很難想像一件事情
In addition, if we know it, we will announce it now
另外我們曉得就會說我們現在公告的
Why announce land restrictions? Mainly the so-called land tax increase
公告土地限制幹嘛?主要是課程所謂的土增稅
This has a notice of land restrictions
這有講公告土地限制
It is the tax authority for landowners
它是稅政機關針對土地所有人
It is used as the basis for land value appreciation when the land is sold and sold
在土地買賣轉動時用以合克土地增值的基礎
it is tuned once a year
它每年的調一次
now you can come and look for it
現在你可以過來找還好
fine
還好
That is to say, the tone is not as low as imagined.
就是說調的等於是並沒有想像那麼低
The announcement limit is equal to the announcement limit adjustment, which is close to the market price, about 80 or so
公告限制等於是公告限制調的算是接近市價大概到80幾
Like Taipei City to 89
像台北市到89
New Taipei City to 89
新北市到89
Anyway, other places are okay
其他地方反正都是還好
This is when we know that you buy and sell land
這個是我們曉得就是說你買賣土地的時候
There is a benchmark for the course
有一個就是說課程的一個基準
Curriculum Benchmarks
課程的基準
but let's look at another
但我們另外看一個
what would you look like if you held land
你持有土地的話你大概是怎麼樣
This gap is quite big
這個差距就蠻大
What is the main purpose of announcing the land price?
公告地價主要是幹嘛?
Announcement of land ownership by all persons during the land holding period
就公告土地所有全人在土地持有期間
It has to pay a tax, which is the announced land price
它必須要繳一個稅,這個就是公告地價
We just bought and sold land, you have to pay a land increase tax, land value-added tax
我們剛剛是買賣土地的,你要繳一個土增稅,土地增值稅
But if you own land, for example, if you own a house, you probably own land
但你持有土地的話,譬如你有房子的話,你大概就持有土地
For land, you have to pay a land value tax
土地的話,你要繳一個地價稅
The land value tax is adjusted every three years
這個地價稅的話,是每三年調整一次
In other words, only once every three years
換句話說,每三年才調整一次
And you see, the gap between the market price and the market price is quite large, the gap between the market price is quite large
而且你看,跟市價之間差距就蠻大,市價之間差蠻大
In other words, if you own the house, especially the land
換句話說,你持有房子,特別是土地的話
The holding cost is not high, simply put
那個持有成本之上是不高的,簡單講
If we discuss it with our colleagues, maybe you own a car
我們跟同事討論的話就曉得,搞不好你擁有一輛車子
You pay more taxes than you pay on owning a house
你繳的稅還比你擁有一棟房子繳的稅還來得高
In other words, what you pay every year is what you pay for your car
換句話說,你每年繳的那個,就是你車子的那個什麼
Not a license plate tax, but also fuel fees
不是有一個牌照的稅,還有燃料費的什麼
Then the sum might be higher than the one you paid, even the tax you paid with a house
那加起來搞不好比你繳的那個,用一棟房子繳的稅都還來高
is this really reasonable
這實在是不是很合理
it's not very reasonable
這不是很合理
Let's take a look at this picture and tell us that
我們看一下這個圖也告訴我們說
If we take three years and 100 years in 2000 as a machine
假如我們以2000年三年100年為作一個機器
Check out this change
來看一下這個的變化
This is an index of a new house
這個是一個新房屋的一個指數
That is three years and 120 years in 2000
就是2000年三年120年
You can see the index words
你可以看到這個指數的話
If the red is the index
這個紅色這個指數的話
Of course it has risen to about 270 now
當然它現在已經漲到大概是270吧
about 270
大概270
But also with this 2000 three-year 100 units
但同樣以這個2000年三年100單位
you use a land appreciation tax
你用一個土地增值稅
Or underground tax house tax
或地下稅房屋稅來比的話
You see, it might be better to increase the tax on this land
你看大概這個土增稅還比較好
Land tax increase should be this, but unpredictable
土增稅應該這個就是難測這個
About 160 170
大概到160 170
But this underground tax
但是這個地下稅
just to put it simply
就簡單講一下就是說
When we were young, the modernization rule increased the price and returned the goods
我們小時候的現化規定漲價歸貨
It is obvious from this soil
從這個土就可以明顯告訴你
The price increase did not return the goods at all
漲價根本就沒有歸貨
Because it's so long
因為長那麼多了嘛
but the really broken parts
但是真正碎碎的部分
It's quite a big difference from before.
還跟這個之前差距還蠻大的
quite a big gap
差距蠻大的
I just said it was
我剛才說等於是
Our government is violating the constitution
我們政府都是在違背憲法
tantamount to violating the constitution
等於是違反憲法規定
to grow back
要長下回光
Tell you from this picture
從這個圖就告訴你
It didn't last long at all.
根本就沒有長下回光嘛
big gap
差距蠻大
OK
OK
what we just said
那我們剛剛講過
There is a problem with the lock
鎖著碎有問題
Not as good as expected
沒有想像中那麼好
what to do
怎麼辦
My idea of ​​paying is to say
我一個出錢想法就是說
Property tax should be a good tax object
財產稅應該是不錯的一個課稅對象
tax object
課稅對象
think about it
你想想看
He escaped in the lock
他在鎖著碎當中逃掉
i didn't pay
我沒有繳到
but he might go buy some real estate
但他可能去買一些房地產
The real estate is right there
這房地產就擺在那邊
Real estate is something you can see and touch.
房地產這個東西是看得到摸得到的
not the same as locked
不跟鎖得一樣
You have to think about how much this person has locked up
你要想得這個人有多少鎖得
it's hard for you to imagine
你還很難想得的
We call Property Pharma Center's Property Declaration Pharmacy
我們叫財產製藥中心的財產申報製藥的
The rules may not be so accurate
守則搞不好不是那麼準
But property I think is pretty accurate
但財產我想是很準的
Because any property you make is where
因為哪一筆財產你做都在哪裡
it is very clear
這是很清楚的
Moreover, our small Taiwan adopts a registration system
而且我們小的台灣是採用登記制
That is, you probably wouldn't easily register in someone else's name, would you?
就是你大概不會輕易地登記在別人名下吧
Presumably your property is registered in your name
大概就你的財產就登記在你的名下
That property is clearly over there
那個財產是很明顯擺在那邊的
over there
擺在那邊的
So I think this should be taught to him
所以這個我覺得應該給他課
Equal to that you may be in the code so not paid
等於是你可能在守則所以沒有繳到
Now the property is over there
現在財產擺在那邊
And we call it property, what characteristics does it have?
而且我們叫財產它有個特色什麼特色
it's right there
就是它就擺在那邊
over there
擺在那邊
what your class rules say
你課守則說的話
If it's a heavy lesson
它還課比較重的話
It's also a lesson
它還課淘調
or become more difficult to move
或變得比較難動
But now the property is over there
但現在財產就擺在那邊
What is the characteristic of this in terms of taxation?
這個在稅子上有個特色是什麼特色
This is distortion is relatively small this tax
這個是distortion是比較小的這個稅
because it's right there
因為它就擺在那邊
it may of course have a sequela
它當然可能有一個後遺症
It's what you might think of after your class
就是你一課之後可能大家想到
That means you step on the past to accumulate property again
就是說你又踩過去累積財產
not so good
不那麼好啦
have this sequelae
有這個後遺症
But now it's over there
但現在是擺在那邊
over there
擺在那邊
It's worth the lesson
搞不好很值得課
well worth the lesson
很值得課
So this is equivalent to saying
所以這個等於就是說
That is to say, the pieces of your hand didn’t reach that part
就是說你手的碎沒有碼到那一部分
your property is visible
你財產是可以看得到
Is it possible to use the broken part of the property
是不是可以用財產碎的那一部分
To make up for the lack of broken hands
來補充這個手的碎的不足
And it means that our small financial distribution is uneven now
而且等於是我們現在小的財務分配不平均
Uneven financial distribution
財務分配不平均
So it might be a good idea to tax the wealth and people
所以課財人稅搞不好是一個不錯的想法
Another idea is to pay taxes
另外想法就是小為稅
small for tax
小為稅的話
Our small class method of course has two methods
我們小的課程方法當然有兩個方法
One is like America
一個就是像美國一樣
only in the last stage
就只在最後那個階段
tax when you spend
你消費的時候課稅
just consume
就消費
This is like Taiwan and the European Union
這個就是像台灣跟歐盟一樣
we call it business value tax
我們把它叫做營業價值稅
for each stage
就對每一階段
taxation of part of the value
價值的部分課稅
but we know your total value in the endgame
但我們曉得你在最後階段的總價值
Is it the same value as yours?
跟你每一段的價值是一樣的嘛
So it is generally believed that
所以這個一般認為就是說
No matter you are in the United States, you are tracking
不管你是美國的在追蹤
Sales Tax for Stage Courses
階段課程的銷售稅
Or the so-called business value tax in the EU and Taiwan
或歐盟跟台灣這個所謂的營業價值稅
Its main difference is that it is equal to
它主要的差別在於等於是
It's right to add a difference in means
激增了一個手段上的不同就對了
collect in one segment
一個分段來收
It's still the last stage to collect
還是最後那個階段來收
less than two basically
不至兩個基本上
You can think of it like it's a consumption tax
你都可以把它想成它是一個消費稅
sale tax
消費稅
It is generally considered a regressive tax
一般認為它是一個累退稅
So it's generally considered a bad tax
所以一般的話認為它是不好的稅
right
對不對
it is a regressive tax
它是一個累退稅
but this point of view
但這個觀點
I don't think that's right
我覺得可能不是那麼對的
how to say
怎麼講呢
point in time to observe
時間上的某一點去觀察
is indeed
就是的確是
This is a regressive tax. Why is it a regressive tax?
這是一個累退稅 為什麼是累退稅呢
Because those who kept higher
因為當年守得比較高者
Because if you consume it, you are done eating, right?
因為消費的話你就是吃完了嘛
finished eating
吃完了的話
like eating
譬如說吃的話
your stomach is that big
你的胃就是那麼大
you can't eat a lot
你不可能吃很多嘛
There is probably a limit to how well you eat.
吃得多好大概也是有限嘛
For example, a rich person like Guo Taiming
比如說像郭台銘那麼有錢的人
you eat well
你吃得
Anyway, his defense is dozens or hundreds of times better than mine
反正他的守得是我好幾十倍或好幾百倍
But he probably only eats mine
但他吃的大概就只有我的
only my double or double
只有我的一倍多或兩倍
he spent money
他花了錢
Because this is a very real problem
因為這個是很現實的問題
because you eat
因為你吃的話
your stomach is that big
你的胃就是那麼大
So if we look at it from the perspective of a certain time period
所以假如從一個某一個時段觀點來看的話
He is indeed a regressive
他的確是一個累退稅
Because of the consumption proportion of the master's starting hand
因為高手的當起手的消費比重
is relatively low
是比較低的
Excluding the specific gravity is relatively high
除去比重是比較高的
Conversely, if you keep low
反過來說你守得比較低的話
Like when I compare with Guo Taiming
像我跟郭台銘比的話
His removal rate must be much higher than mine
他除去率一定比我高很多
I'm relatively low handed
我是比較低手的
When starting the consumption and removing the proportion
當起手的消費的跟除去比重
will
就會
In other words, consumption is higher
換句話說消費就比較高
If I remove it, the proportion will be lower
我除去就會比重就比較低
But since GST is a proportional tax
但是由於消費稅是一個比例稅
Consumption tax is a tax on consumption
消費稅只針對消費部分客稅
There is no tax on the outgoing part
並沒有對出去部分客稅
Therefore, the proportion of consumption in the current income is relatively low
所以當期所得中消費比重比較低者
He is a master
就是他高手者
Those who spend more than the current income will be lower-handed
比當期所得中消費比較高者就低手者
Taxes that pay a relatively large proportion of income
角納得比較大的所得比重的稅乎
In other words, Porteimon, for example
換句話說波台門譬如說
He earns hundreds of millions each
他每個收入幾億
His consumption may be, for example, 10 million
他消費可能是有譬如1000萬
My income may be, say, 100,000
我收入可能譬如說10萬好了
I spend maybe 50,000
我消費可能到5萬
Look at the proportion of the digger, he spends 10 million out of 100 million
你看就比重挖員他一億裡面消費1000萬
10 million is very high
1000萬算是很高的
But compared to 100 million
但跟一億來比的話
just one tenth
就十分之一
But my words say 100,000
但我的話譬如說10萬
When the spend reaches 60,000
當花到6萬
I'm six out of ten
我就十分之六
So the proportion of my payment is obviously higher than that of buying Taiwan doors
所以我繳的比重很顯然比購台門來高
So most people think this tax is a bad tax
所以是一般人認為這個稅是不好的稅
it is a view on regressive taxation
它是累退稅上的一個看法
but let's think about it
但我們想想看
People don't just live in a certain world, they live in a very long time
人不是只有活在某一個世界,他是很長的時間的
It's hard to say if you don't care about the Middle Ages
從中世不關你來看的話,這就很難講
How should I put it? First, if you compare at a certain point in time
怎麼說呢?第一個,你在時間上某一點來比的話
When you start with a high score and a low score, it is probably related to your age
當起手的是高分低的話,很可能是跟你的年齡有關的
For example, if you think about it, when you first entered the workplace, your salary must not be high
譬如你想想,你剛進入職場的時候,你的薪水一定不高
Conversely, when you retire, you have no salary at that time, so the lockup must be relatively low
反過來你退休的時候,你那時候沒薪水,鎖得一定比較低
Conversely, when you are in your fifties or sixties, your salary is at its peak
反過來你在五六十歲的時候,你的薪水是最高峰
So at that time, young people paid a higher proportion of consumption tax and consumption tax.
所以那時候年輕人繳的稅,消費稅繳的比重比較高
Or the consumption tax paid by the elderly is relatively high, and the tax paid by people in their fifties and sixties will be relatively low
或老人人繳的消費稅比較高,五六十歲那種人繳的稅會比較低
This is purely the number of years, purely the number of years
這個純粹是年年年數,純粹是年年數
Because you are young and you will be fifty or sixty one day
因為你年輕人有一天也會到五六十歲
Fifty or sixty years old will retire one day
五六十歲有一天也會退休
So this is the peak
所以這個來看的話比較高峰
If you want to get up, be your own, so in other words
要起來的話 當起所的 所以換句話說
A result of the different cycles of this life
這個生命不同周期所造成的一個
It's right to be a gap
當起所的一個差距就對了
So at a certain point in time you watch this
所以從時間上某一點你去看 這個
Observe with you from a person's life
跟你從一個人的一生去觀察
This is different, you see
這個是不大一樣 你看
What will you do with the money you earn in your life
你一生賺的錢你會怎麼用
what will happen to you you will eventually run out
你會怎麼樣 你最後一定會全部用光光
How should I put it, eat it and spend it if you want
怎麼說呢 你要嘛就吃完了 花掉
Either donate to your child
要嘛就捐贈給你的小孩
or leave an inheritance to your children
或留下遺產給你的小孩
Just leave a legacy to donate this thing
只要留下遺產捐贈這個東西
can be counted as an expense
都可以把它算成一種花費
words with some form of consumption
某種形式的消費的話
You just spend your money, right?
你就是花光光嘛 對吧
you are in the middle of your life
你在一生所的當中
You're done eating again, right?
你又消費吃完了 對呀
But you might just pass the money on to your kids
但你可能就是把錢轉給你的小孩
or bequeath to your children
或遺贈給你的小孩
But it would be nice to leave that bequest
但把那個遺贈也好
Or change hands
或是轉手也好
see it as some kind of
都把它看成某種
Formal consumption, because a tax will be levied for a while
形式的消費,因為一陣也好都要課一個稅嘛
you see it as a form of consumption
你把它看成某種形式的一個消費的話
I think it is more reasonable to say that this tax is basically a proportional tax
我覺得比較合理的就是說這個稅基本上它是一個比例稅
Because the end of my middle hand is all spent?
因為我中間手的最後花光光嘛
you see from a certain practice
你從某一個實踐來看
it is a tax refund
它是一個理退稅
If you look at it from the point of view of your life, what is the end of your life?
在你從一生觀點來看的話,你一生所的最後怎麼樣
spend it in some form
都以某種形式花掉嘛
Speaking of those forms, we all regard it as some kind of consumption
講那些形式我們都把它看成某種消費
We will give it a lesson on that consumption
那個消費我們都給它課一個
For example, consumption tax
比如說消費稅的話
For example, if we talk about the tax for a while, we will impose a proportional tax of 10%.
譬如說一陣稅的話我們給它課一個比例稅10%的
At least now than consumption tax
現在至少比消費稅來
The consumption tax rate is still high, because the consumption tax is now 5%
消費稅率還高啊,因為消費稅現在是5%啊
Because it's 5%, now
因為是5%啊,現在
It’s been 10% for a while, it’s even higher than that
這一陣子是10%啊,都比它還高啊
So in a way
所以從某種程度來看的話
From the point of view of life, maybe it is not a person
從一生觀點來看的話,可能它就不是一個人
not alone
不是一個人
And in fact someone did a study
而且事實上有人做過研究
It turns out that from a lifetime point of view
它證明出來就是說從終身觀點來看
Maybe from a certain experiment, for example, this year
可能從某一個實驗譬如說今年來看的話
it's really different
就的確是不一樣
words from a lifelong point of view
從終身觀點來看的話
Its discovery is that
它的發現就是說
in fact a billy tax
事實上是一個比利稅
and it even has a D
而且它甚至有一個D
even a bump
甚至有一個坎坷
I don't want you to be rough, right?
你這個坎坷就我不要對不對
it says even a little tired
它說甚至有點累晉
I don't know what's the reason for this tiredness
我不曉得這個累晉什麼原因
But basically you can imagine
不過基本上你可以想像得到
From a lifetime perspective, this tax
這個稅從終身觀點來看的話
I think billy tax is more reasonable
我覺得比利稅是比較合理的
Billy tax is more reasonable
比利稅是比較合理的
In a certain experiment, the height of your hand is D
在某一實驗上你手的高有D
For example, like when I was just now
譬如像我剛剛的時候
When you are middle-aged, of course you earn more money
你中年的時候你賺的錢當然比較多
when you were young
你在年輕的時候
Of course, when you are old, you earn less money
年老的時候賺的錢當然比較少
So from this point of view
所以從這個觀點來看的話
The tax you pay is higher
你繳那的稅手的比較高
So the tax will be lower
所以繳那的稅會比較低
Because you spend less
因為你花的比重比較低
more when you were young
更你在年輕的時候
spend more money
花的錢比較多
So the tax is heavier
所以繳的稅比較重
This is purely a matter of age
這個純粹是年齡民所
words from a lifelong point of view
從終身觀點來看的話
i think it should be a billy tax
我覺得它應該是個比利稅
This is what I want to emphasize
這一點也是我要強調
may be
可能就是
Talk to us about consumption tax in general
跟我們一般談到消費稅的話
Generally the strongest objection is that
一般最強烈的反對理由就是說
it is a tax refund
它是一個理退稅
at least i don't think so
至少我覺得應該不是
I think it should be a more reasonable view
我覺得它應該是一個比較合理的看法
from a lifelong perspective
從終身觀點來看
You keep it all your life and spend it all in the end
你終身守得到最後就全部花光光
And I will give you a certain percentage if I spend all of it
而且花光光我都給你某一個比例的話
it is a proportional tax
它就是一個比例稅
if so
假如是這樣的話
Then there is another view as we said earlier
那麼有另外一個看法就像我們前面所說的
That is to say, there are probably many of us
就是說這個大概我們很多
probably all
大概都是
That is, many of the taxes paid are payroll taxes.
就是繳的稅當中很多都是薪資稅
salary
薪水
So here we have a profile
那麼這裡我們有一個資料
have a profile
有一個資料
That is to say, with the past two years
就是說我們以這兩年的
Two years of tax returns
兩年的報稅資料來看
The salary is about
薪資所的大概是
On our tax return it's about 75%
在我們的報稅資料大概是75%
That is to say, in our tax filing
就是說我們報稅資料上當中
belonging to the payroll
屬於薪資所的
Based on the data of the past two years
用這兩年資料來看的話
on average
在平均
average about
平均大概是
This should be a photo
這個應該是照吧
Hundreds of billions
千億嘛 照
More than three trillion, that's probably, the mental part,
三兆多,那都大概,心思部分,
In other words, about 15% of the mind part of our New Year's materials
換句話說,我們抱歲資料的心思部分大概占15%
The non-mental part is about one trillion,
非心思所的部分大概是一兆,
In other words, the three trillion and one trillion account for about 25%
換句話說,這個三兆這個一兆大概是占到25%
If we compare this information with the United States,
這個資料假如我們跟美國,
Compared with other European countries,
其他歐洲國家來比的話,
How about it? In the United States, if we also use the data of the past two years to look at it,
大概怎麼樣,美國我們同樣用這兩年資料來看的話,
The ratio of its mind to movement is about 56.3,
它心思所的比動大概56.3,
In other words, less than 60%
換句話說,還不到60%
About 43% after non-psychological ratio
非心思比之後大概43%
If we look at the OECD countries in Europe,
假如我們歐洲的OECD的國家來看,
Using the data of the past two years for comparison,
用這兩年資料來比,
It's even lower than this,
它甚至這個更低,
less than, in other words, half and half,
還不到,換句話說一半一半,
In other words, on the information about the age,
換句話說,在抱歲資料上,
data presented in other countries,
在其他國家呈現出來的資料,
My thoughts are not so high,
心思所的沒那麼高,
However, the ratio shown in our Taiwan data is quite high,
但是我們台灣的資料呈現出來的比例蠻高的,
about 75%,
大概75%,
If you compare it with the United States,
你看跟美國來比的話,
Can you see it or not?
可以看不看得到呢?
For example, if you think of it as sixty-four
這個譬如說你把它想成六十四十
This is about half and half
這個大概一半一半
But Taiwan's words seventy-five-eight
但台灣的話七十五八
what is this manifestation
這個顯現是什麼東西
means that part of our non-new place
就表示我們這個非新之所的部分
probably a lot
大概很多很多
Probably didn't get it
大概都沒有掌握到
Then what is a primary idea
然後一個初選想法是什麼想法
The primary idea is that we know
這初選想法就是我們曉得
what you earn is your income
你賺的所的這是你的收入面
Another time you will spend
另外一個時候你會花掉
This is your consumer side
這是你的消費面
I just said the words spent
我剛剛講過花掉的話
you think of it as a generalized flower
你把它想成一個廣義的花
For example, the inheritance you leave to your children
譬如說你留給小孩的遺產
You end up spending it too
你最後也把它算成花掉
Here we have an income tax
這邊我們有一個就所得稅
Here we have an excise tax or business value tax
這邊我們有一個消費稅或營業價值稅
in other words
換句話說
Income side of your income
對你的所得的收入面
I carve an income tax
我刻一個所得稅
on the side of where you get paid
對你所得的發費之處那一面
I engrave a GST
我刻一個消費稅
Taiwan called business value tax
台灣叫營業價值稅
If we don't have a good grasp of this aspect of keeping
假如我們在守的這方面沒有掌握得很好
From the data point of view, it is not well grasped
從資料上來看沒有掌握得很好
Can we start from the side of consumption
我們是不是可以從消費的這一面
cover him partly
把他部分把它cover 回來
And this side feels like Shinnomori's stand is busy and high
而且這一面感覺上就是新之守的站得比較忙高的
So this guard is probably as you can imagine
所以這部守的大概可以想像中
Mostly you can think of him as a new tax guard
大部分你就可以把想成他是一個新之守的稅
Therefore, there may be a gap in Taiwan's tax compliance.
所以台灣的守的稅大致當然可能有一個差距
He still has 25% he is not a non-new guard
他還有25%他不是非新之守的
Roughly you can imagine that it mainly comes from Shinnoshu
大致你可以把想像中主要就來自新之守的
But on the other hand, consumption tax
但這一面的話要消費稅
So a basic idea is to say
所以一個基本想法就是說
You missed the tax on this side
這一面守的稅你漏掉了
But when you spend you still spend
但你花的時候還是要花
So guarding this missing part I didn't engrave it
所以守著這個漏掉的部分我沒有刻到
can i spend time from you
我是不是可以從你花費的時候
I cover you back
我把你cover 回來
because you're guarding this side now
因為你現在守著這方面
Basically this new information guards the tax
基本上這個新資訊守著稅
There are a lot of guards missing
有很多守著漏掉了嘛
That is to say, there are structural problems
也就是說有結構上的問題
There are so many holes in the chamber
有膛中有穴特別多
open economy again
又是開放經濟
so your class that tax is a bit difficult
所以你的課那個稅有點困難
But you still have to spend it if you want to eat it hot
但你要吃完熱還是要花掉
so spend this part
所以花掉這部分
This aspect is equal to your taxes, for example,
這方面等於是你這邊稅金譬如說
If you have raised it here, for example, within 1,000 yuan
你這邊漲過它的話譬如說1000塊當中
You only go up to say 700 yuan
你只漲到譬如說700塊
You missed 300 yuan
有300塊你漏掉了
But it still has to spend out of the 1000
但1000塊當中它還是要花掉
here when it's spent
花掉的時候這邊
can i raise it back
我是不是可以把它漲回來
and it feels like
而且感覺是要等於是
Here you have raised to 7000 yuan
這邊你漲過到7000塊
but on this side
但這一邊的話
you may be 1000 yuan
你可能是1000塊
your tax is bigger
你的稅金比較大
So the basic idea is to say
所以基本想法就是說
can i get it back from the other side
是不是我可以從另外後面把它拿回來
get it back like this
這樣拿回來
This is probably my most basic idea
這個大概有我一個最基本的想法
the idea
這個想法
you look first
你先看
As long as the so-called tax is the new tax
只要是所謂稅是新的稅金
If your salary is taxable, if your salary is taxable
新資守得稅的話,新資守得稅的話
What is the gap between you and your sales tax?
跟你用銷的稅來課,差距在哪裡?
The difference is that if you have accumulated financial resources now,
差在就是說,你現在假如有累積財務的話,
If you accumulate finances, for example, if you have several houses,
累積財務的話,比如你有好幾棟房子,
Keeping the tax is not a lesson to us,
守得稅是課不到我們的,
Because it's basically a payroll tax,
因為它基本上是新資守得稅,
In other words, if we determine that Taiwan's Shou De tax,
換句話說,假如我們認定台灣的守得稅,
Basically, if a new capital keeps tax,
基本上是一個新資守得稅的話,
Your wealth need not be taxed,
你那些財富是不必小稅,
You don't have to keep the tax, it's right, you can't pay the tax, it's right,
不必小守得稅,就對了,課不到那個稅就對了,
But if you turn it into sales tax, I can get it,
但是你把它轉成銷的稅的話,我就可以課到,
Why can I attend class?
為什麼我可以課到呢?
Because sooner or later all your life will be spent,
因為你終身所得遲早都會花掉,
So we will also send out in this house
所以我們在這房子也會發掉
How to send it away?
怎麼發掉呢?
He might just sell it or leave it to his son
他可能就把它賣掉或留遺產給他兒子
but anyway
但不管怎麼樣
For those corners, we consider him to be a kind of consumption
那些角我們把他認定他是消費一種消費的話
From the consumption fee, we can still keep it from flying
從消費費當中我們仍然可以把它卡不飛來
So this is payroll tax versus excise tax
所以這是薪資所的稅跟消費稅
I think one of the biggest differences
我覺得一個最大的一個不同
In other words, if you use the payroll tax
換句話說假如你採用薪資所的稅的話
In other words, what tax do you pay?
換句話說你繳的稅什麼
You have to pay taxes when you work at a young age
就年輕工作的時候是要繳稅
wait till old age
等到年老的時候
You don’t have to pay for every few accounts
你每幾個財務你就不必繳了
because hand tax
因為手都稅
Pay as we just said
繳像我們剛剛講的
It's basically a payroll tax
它基本上是一個薪資所的稅的話
you were making money when you were young
你在賺錢年輕的時候
You have to pay this tax on the money you earn
你賺的錢你就必須要繳這個稅
But you don't have to pay every few financial
但你每幾個財務就不必繳了
On the contrary, if you pay consumption tax
相反的繳是消費稅的話
what kind of personality does it have
它有個性的什麼樣
Because consumption tax means
因為消費稅就是說
You have to pay for what you consume
你消費掉的東西你就必須要繳
If I just imagine
假如我一把想像從
Say you leave a house for your son
比如說你留一棟房子給你的兒子
It's also a form of consumption
這也是某種形式的消費的話
That consumption tax can be taught
那個消費稅是可以課導的
But the tax of the workshop is not covered
但是修制所的稅是課不到的
And here I have quoted this article
而且這裡我有引用這篇文章
he has an opinion
他就有一個看法
It is said that wealth is not equal to the wealth of a society
說財富繳一個社會財富不平均的話
uneven words
不平均的話
Consumption tax is better than lock tax
消費稅上是比鎖的稅還好
Why? Because wealth is uneven
為什麼?因為財富不平均的話
Your locked tax payment is basically a new lock tax
你鎖的稅繳基本上是一個新式鎖的稅的話
Wealth is tantamount to being useless
對財富是等於是派不上用場的
unless you like what we said earlier
除非你像我們前面講的
can a property tax
可以一個財產稅
Property tax is of course more direct
財產稅當然更直接
But if the property tax cannot be paid
但是財產稅繳辦不到的話
Consumption tax is tantamount to indirect eight-and-a-half guide
消費稅等於是可以間接八共以半導
because when you want to consume
因為當你要消費的時候
For example, you may sell your house to make a consumption
比如說你可能賣掉房子去做一個消費
bequeath that house to your son
把那個房子留遺產給你的兒子
If we regard all these as a consumption
假如這些種種我們都把它看成一個消費的話
And we do make these things on the tax system
而且我們的確在稅制上做出這些東西
We all have words for it
我們都有給它課到的話
Excise taxes are actually better improvements than locked-in taxes
消費稅事實上比鎖的稅更能改善
Lock separation Financial separation
鎖的分別 財務分別
because of the wealth of those ages
因為那些年紀的財富
You can't pay the tax for the new lock
你新之鎖的稅是課不到
Because you only get this tax when you are in the new lock
因為只有在新之鎖的時候你才課到這個稅
But consumption tax can be imposed
但消費稅可以課到
Why?
可以課到 為什麼呢
because of your finances
因為你這些財務
In the end it will be spent in some form
最後還是以某種形式會花掉
Like leaving an inheritance to your son
比如說留遺產給你的兒子
or will spend in some form
或者以某種形式會花掉
once spent
一旦花費的話
If we interpret it as an expense in a relatively broad sense
假如我們把它解釋成花費是一個比較廣義的花費的話
Consumption tax can be taxed to this tax
消費稅就可以課到這個稅
class to this tax
課到這個稅
and he thinks
而且他認為
If a society's finances are uneven
假如一個社會財務又不平均的話
GST is a better tax
消費稅是更好的一個稅
right
是吧
because of the financial part
因為那個財務的部分
Sales tax is available
銷售稅是能夠課到的
Where's your tax?
你手的稅呢
If it is a salary hand tax
假如是薪資手的稅
If it belongs to the tax nature of salary hand
屬於薪資手的稅性質的話
Less than this class
這課不到
So my idea is to say
那麼我一個想法就是說
we are small now
我們現在小的就是說
If we are now in Taiwan
我們現在台灣的話
In Taiwan, it is business
台灣的話就是營業
Business value is now 5%
營業價值現在是5%
5%
5%
Then my idea is to say
然後我一個想法就是說
Because my property tax is used to make up for the lack of helper's tax
因為我財產稅來補助手的稅的不足
Because the property is there
因為財產就擺在那邊了
This person has accumulated
這個人已經累積完了
After the accumulation is over, it is like the land
累積完了就跟土地一樣
right there
就擺在那邊了
over there words
擺在那邊的話
if you pay taxes again
你再課稅的話
From the point of view of education
從學歷上來看的話
no efficiency loss
是沒什麼效率損失的
because he has accumulated
因為他已經累積完了
before you accumulate
你在累積之前
he will affect that is to say
他會影響就是說
Do I want to accumulate
我要不要累積
For example, you now announce that
譬如說你現在宣布說
I am now for his property
我現在對於他財產
I have to pay heavier taxes
我要課比較重的稅
what will he affect
他會影響哪些的
Affect those who have not yet accumulated
影響哪些還沒有累積的人
or those who want to accumulate
或想要累積的人
for those who have accumulated
對於那些已經累積的人
he was not
他是沒有被
fully manageable
完全應付的
Because once the government announces
因為政府一旦宣布
For example, for each household, I now add it to the moderator of the middle school
譬如說每戶我現在把它加中課版主的話
it has a phenomenon
它就有一個現象
This is what we call capitalization
這是我們把它叫做capitalization
What is capitalization?
什麼叫capitalization呢
What is the value of your house
就是你一東房子的價值什麼
The value of a house is
一東房子的價值就是
You can generate income in the future
未來可以讓你產生收益
This income includes the income you live in
這個收益包括你自己住的那個收益
Also includes the proceeds that you can rent out
也包括你可以出租的那個收益
This is what this house is worth
這個就是這一棟房子的價值
you live alone
你自己住
Or you can rent it out to someone else
或者你可以出租給別人住
you can collect this income
你可以收這個收入
Think about it, once the government collects taxes
你想想看政府一旦課稅之後
what does it mean
是什麼意思呢
means, for example, that every month you
就表示譬如說你每個月
Originally, the rent could have been, say, 20,000 yuan.
本來租金可以譬如說兩萬塊
I can take a class now
現在可以課個
It's like a little bit of 20,000 yuan
等於是有一點點兩萬塊當中
The government took 5,000 yuan
五千塊就政府就拿去了
what is this wish
這個意願什麼東西
You could have rented your house at 20,000 yuan a month
你本來每個月的房子你可以收租到兩萬塊
Once the government announces that
現在政府一旦宣布說
Out of the 20,000, I can collect 5,000.
兩萬塊當中我可以收五千塊
including real estate
包括房地產
It means that the value of each root of your house is only 15,000
就表示你這段房子的每根的價值只剩下15000
15,000 for each 15,000 if you fly it back
15000每根15000你把它倒飛回去的話
The value of this section of the house will drop immediately
這段房子的價值馬上就下跌
we fall
我們按著下跌
This is the capitalization of our education
這個就是我們學歷上的capitalization
capitalization
capitalization
So this poor means
所以這個poor的就是說
ok
ok
what we say
我們的說法
that is
就是說
right now
就是目前
That is to say, directly tax the finances
就是說對財務直接課稅
Of course it is a better way
當然是比較好的一個方式
but if not
但假如不行的話
we can retire as a planner
我們可以退休求計師
Make a correction from the consumption tax
從消費稅上來做一個補正
Of course our current consumption tax rate is 5%
當然我們目前的消費稅率是5%
The tax rate of hand tax is of course much higher
手額稅的稅率當然是高很多
so how to correct
所以怎麼補正
One of my thoughts is to say
我一個出現想法就是說
Is it possible to treat all consumer goods as
是不是可以把所有的消費品當作
Two-level cargo industry
貨業兩級
one is normal
一個是正常品
One is a high-end product like this
一個是高級品這樣
Let's give it five boards for the blue bottle
這藍瓶我們就給它板子五
For high-end bottles, we will give them a relatively high breakage rate, and the board will be ten.
高級瓶我們就給它課一個比較高的碎率就板子十
At present, we want to talk about the provisions of the business tax law
目前的話我們想要談的營業稅法規定
The applicable tax rate for the business tax rate is the lowest board, the board with the highest five boards
營業稅率適用稅率是最低是板子五最高的板
There is administrative luck in this tax increase
這個增加稅率有行政運氣
In case you want to mention board five, just prove
萬一要提到板子五只要證明
I declared to myself that if I want class five, I don’t have to go through the Legislative Yuan.
自己宣佈說我要課板子五就不必經過立法院就對了
What I'm breaking down here is to say
我這裡破文的就是說
Is it possible to divide our consumer products into two categories
有沒有可能把我們的消費產品分成兩類
One is more commonly used
一個是比較大家常用的
One is a relatively high-end bottle
一種是比較高級瓶
Can be divided into two categories
可以分這兩類
So the basic idea is something like
所以基本的想法就有點說
Is it necessary to expand the current facility tax to a relatively large extent?
是不是把目前的設施稅做一個比較大的擴充
This is probably the most basic idea
這是大概一個最基本的想法
So the overall source
所以整體來源
I'd say it's probably the first
我要說的大概就是第一個
It is very problematic on the tax of the hand
它的手的稅上是很有問題
Not as good as we thought
沒有我們想像中那麼好
from the tax system
從報稅制要上
Let's see, from the competition plan
來看,從那個競兵方案來看
Feeling, of course, is full of problems
感覺當然就是說滿有問題
So since there is a problem
所以既然是有問題的話
So in terms of the design of Suizhi
所以在碎智的設計上的話
We're going to have a whole new, different idea
我們要有一個全新的一個不同想法
And the question I think
而且這個問題我覺得
It's not that any one person can solve the problem
不是說任何一個人上台能夠解決
it's a structural problem
這是結構性的問題
Because there are so many Chinese series in Taiwan
因為台灣中華系列就特別多
those people are amazing
那些人都很厲害
You have to tax some people in Taiwan
台灣有些人你要給他課稅
not so easy
也不是那麼容易
it's a structural problem
這是結構性的問題
It's not that the government doesn't work hard
不是說這個政府不努力
effort or not
努力不努力的問題
like the words in the American data
像美國資料上的話
Sale Importment
Sale Importment
It ran away with 57 out of 100
它100塊當中57塊跑掉
America should be a very advanced country
像美國應該是很先進的國家
Although it is the whole world to find
它雖說是全世界去找
You are a U.S. citizen in Taiwan
你在台灣的美國公民
you have to pay taxes
你要繳稅
it's pretty awesome
它算是很厲害
Look at the 100 yuan
你看100塊當中
57 yuan escaped
57塊都逃落掉
It means that this matter is not so easy to solve
就表示這件事情不是那麼容易解決的
Taiwan is another open economy
台灣又是一個開放經濟
in the words of master
在高手的話
flow fast
流速得很快
Those who are very high should have a lower tax rate
很高的那些人 本來稅率就要應該給他低
From the point of view of education
從學歷上來看
From the point of view of efficiency, it should be low and should not be high
從效率觀點來看 本來就應該低 不應該高
It's not so easy when you tax him
你給他課稅的話 不是那麼容易
So the tax at hand, judging from the data, is there any problem
所以手頭稅 從資料來看 有什麼一個問題
From a structural point of view, it is not so easy to correct him.
從結構性來看 要改正他 不是那麼容易
So for an idea that arises is to say
所以為一個出現想法的就是說
Taiwan's tax structure may have a very different idea
台灣的稅制結構 可能要有一個很不同的一個想法
Can not follow our general academic qualifications
不能依照我們一般學歷的
That is, the idea you read in the textbook
就是說你念的教科書那個想法
to design the tax system
來設計這個稅制
rather than a fair dispute
而不是說要公平爭議
How about I have to tax the masters heavily?
對高手的我就要給他課很重的稅怎麼樣
But maybe when actually executing
但是可能在真正在執行的時候
have a big problem
都有很大一個問題
I'm just saying today
我今天講的只是說
Is it possible to look at it from two perspectives
可不可能從兩個面向來看
from property tax
從財產稅上
It's certainly a nice tax system
這當然是一個很不錯的稅制
he has accumulated over there
他已經累積在那邊了
And wealth inequality is a problem for workers in Greater Asia
而財富對不均又是大西亞工人的問題
If you tax him the stuff accumulated over there
累積在那邊的東西 你給他課稅的話
no efficiency loss
是不會有效率損失的
His loss of efficiency is
他有效率損失的事在
those of the future who are ready to accumulate
未來那些準備累積的人
Because he thought of the tax in the class
因為他就想到說課那麼中的稅
I don't want to accumulate
我就不要累積的
I accumulate less
我累積比較少
will affect
會有影響
but for the accumulated
但對已經累積的
In other words, how many houses do you have now those people
換句話說你現在有幾棟房子那些人
There is actually nothing to lose
實際上是沒有任何損失的
like a piece of land
就跟一塊土地一樣
you put there first
你先擺在那邊
I give you lessons
我給你課
No matter how high the tax is, you have nothing to do
再高的稅你一點辦法都沒有
It's not like saying you're a master of taxation
不像說你是高手的課稅的話
He moves the finances out
他就把財務移出去
He removes all that he gets
他把那個所得什麼全部移出去
This will affect the behavior
這個就會影響到這些行為
you accumulate over there first
你先累積在那邊
I will tax you even higher
我給你課再高的稅
It won't affect your behavior
也不會影響到你的行為了
it's a property tax
這是財產稅
another excise tax
另外一個消費稅
consumption tax
我要說的這個消費稅
He should not be a tax burden
他應該不是一個累費稅
From a lifelong perspective
從一個終身觀的來看的話
you make a definition of consumption
你做一個對消費的定義
to give a broad explanation
做一個廣義的解釋的話
I think it's more reasonable
我覺得比較合理的
because he should be a tax
因為他應該是個比稅
than tax
比稅
while consumption tax
而消費稅
Compared with the tax compliance based on the new capital tax compliance
跟以新資守稅為準的守稅來比的話
he has an advantage
他有個好處
It's your annual financial part.
就是你每年的財務那一部分呢
He can't pay tax on salary
薪資所的稅他是課不到的
GST can be paid by him
消費稅他可以課到
Because sooner or later those finances of yours are going to be spent in some form
因為你那些財務遲早要以某種形式花掉
Once spent, he has some form of consumption
一旦花掉的話他就是有某種消費的形式
once a form of consumption
一旦是某種消費形式的話
Consumption tax has a way to tax this tax
消費稅就有辦法課到這個稅
For a country, as long as the financial distribution becomes more unequal,
對一個國家只要財務分配越不平均的話
Excise tax is actually better than hand tax
消費稅事實上比手的稅還好
But consumption tax we know that the current tax rate is 5% which is low
但消費稅我們曉得目前的稅率是5%偏低
You're going to replace the tax on hands with the GST
你要以消費稅全部取代手的稅
I don't think it's that easy
我覺得不是那麼容易
So a possible solution
所以一個可行的辦法
I think it is possible to divide our consumption into two commodities
我覺得是不是可以把我們的消費分成兩種商品
One is probably more normal
一種是可能比較正常品的
One is more advanced
一種是比較高級品的
We give it two tax rates
我們給它分兩種稅率
Of course, there are many problems in practice and operation.
這個在實務上在運作上當然有很多問題
For example, if you do this
比如說這樣一做的話
Do many people buy through online shopping?
是不是很多人就是透過網購去買
or export to buy
或者是出口去買
Of course, there are very real issues to consider.
這個當然有很現實的問題要考量
very real problem
很現實的問題
It's the opposite of paying
這是出錢相反
OK, I'll probably stop here today
OK 我今天大概講到這裡
we have a little time now to ask questions
我們現在有一點時間來請各位有問題
bring it up with me please cut it short
跟我提出來 請剪短
Thank you teacher for your wonderful speech
謝謝老師精采的演講
What I want to ask is also for the two very brilliant ideas you just mentioned
我想請教的也是針對您剛剛提的兩個非常精采的想法
First property tax
第一 財產稅
Taiwan has the mutual characteristics of small and medium-sized enterprises
台灣這樣有中小企業的這種相互這種特色
The small and medium-sized enterprises serve each other and provide labor services to each other.
那中小企業他互相服務 互相提供勞務
We can't grasp his little sorrow
我們就沒辦法掌握他的小悲愁啦
On the other hand, you just mentioned
那另外一方面是您剛剛有提到
Accumulating wealth is ugly for a person's life
累積財產一個人一生難看的話
Should be a good tax system too
應該也是一個好稅制
But if I am the host of a small and medium-sized enterprise
可是如果我是一個中小企業的主持人
I've been accumulating my fortune in my own business
我就把我的財產一直累積在我自己的那個企業
I don't want to accumulate on me
我不要累積在我的身上
I let my family continue to run the business
我讓我的家族繼續經營這個企業
The property has always been enjoyed by the family
財產就一直讓這個家族享用了
For this part, since he let the legal person accumulate the property
這個部分既然他是把財產讓那個法人累積
He has no other property of his own
他又沒有另外自己做自己的財產
to enjoy consumption
去享受消費
Seems to be uncommon to the property tax
好像不見得客的到財產稅
Or the appearance of the consumption room
或是說消費室的樣子
I maybe you think
我也許你覺得
no matter what
不管怎麼樣
Ask the teacher to tell you your information
請老師說你的資訊
this detail may
這個細節可能
I can't say much
我不能等於是講很多
This is equivalent to
這個等於要
equal to a question on the executive side
等於執行面的一個問題
but what you just said
不過你剛剛講的
I guess we should have rules
我猜想我們應該有規定
You said what you said should be
你說你講的應該是
Similar to the concept of retaining the cloud forest
類似保留雲林的概念
like the money he made
譬如他賺的錢
He continued to accumulate in the company
他就在公司裡面繼續累積
then my understanding
那我的了解
Taiwan seems to have regulations on the preservation of Yunlin
台灣對保留雲林好像也有規定
There is a rule that says
有一個規定就是說
For example, if you accumulate to a certain extent
譬如說你累積到某個程度
he's going to pay a tax or something
他就要課一個稅或怎麼樣
is that he should have one
就是他應該有一個
tantamount to having a
等於是有一個
There should be a relevant provision in this tax law
這個稅法上應該有相關的一個規定
it's impossible to say
就不可能就是說
Then you say to keep all the money in the company
那你就說把錢全部留在公司裡面
continue
繼續
I understand this should
這個我了解應該
should mean
應該就是說
There are relevant provisions in the law
在法律上有相關規定
That probably belongs to Reserve Yunlin
那個大概屬於保留雲林
he may force you to assign
他可能會強迫你分配
or how
或怎麼樣
or if you keep Yunlin too much
或你保留雲林太多的話
he might be able to take a class
他可能可以課一個
There's a retainer and there's a hundred-day tax
有一個保留員也有一個百日子的稅
hundred days tax
百日子的稅
So the previous industry you mentioned in the China region
所以前面那個你說中華區的產業
how are each other
互相之間是怎麼樣
I'm not so clear about this
這個我比較不那麼清楚
But he only needs to consume
不過他只要消費
If he just goes shopping
他只要去買東西的話
if you buy something
買東西的話
He pays that tax
他就繳那個稅啊
Didn't he say for example
不是嗎 他就譬如說
previous hotel
上一個酒店
just post what
就發什麼呀
He has to pay that tax, doesn't he?
他就必須繳那個稅不是嗎
that's a question of performance
那個是發揮上的問題
You just
你只要
just consume
只要消費就對了
just like us
就跟我們一般人一樣
As long as you spend, you have to pay that tax
你只要消費你就必須要付那個稅
i guess your question
我猜想你那個問題
should
應該
I have a hunch that it should be fine.
我一個直覺感覺應該還好
should be fine
應該還好
but maybe some
不過可能有些
That is to say I just came up with an idea
就是說我剛剛提出來只是一個想法
My basic idea is to say
我基本的想法就是說
first flick tax
第一個彈個手的稅
Maybe not as good as expected
可能並沒有想像那麼好
not as good as expected
沒有想像那麼好
Since it is not as good as imagined
既然沒有想像那麼好的話
what is the reason
是什麼原因呢
I feel like a
我自己覺得是一個
structural problems
結構性上的問題
not that you try to
不是說你努力要
What is he trying to change
改變他努力什麼樣
I don't think it's
我覺得這不是
not this question
不是這個問題
In this case
既然這樣的話
I pay alone
我一個出錢
Maybe considering Taiwan's broken intelligence design
可能在考慮台灣的碎智設計上
call a new and different idea
叫一個全新不同的想法
I just said not long ago
我前不久的就是說
We have a colleague who said this
我們有一個同事他有這樣說
he said in japan there is a debris room
他說在日本的話有一個碎物室
i don't know what their name is
我不曉得他們叫什麼呢
debris room
碎物室
his idea is to say
他的想法就是說
Each debris room, for example
每個碎物室譬如說
Responsible for 100 SMEs
負責100家的中小企業
For example, it would be right to only manage 100 companies.
譬如說就專門管著100家就對了
if you can imagine
假如說你可以想像到
I'm in charge of the debris room
有我來負責的碎物室
For example, if there are 100 companies, I will be in charge.
譬如說100家就有我來負責
Maybe you can draw some bonuses
搞不好可能可以抽取一些獎金
For example, I found
譬如說我查到
how old should you be
你應該講那麼多歲
In the end you didn't speak
結果你沒有講
I can draw some bonuses
我就可以抽取一些獎金
inject strength
注入實力
i really want
我實在想
Can't do well in Taiwan
在台灣搞不好
For example, when we were young, we were so rich and strong
譬如說我們小時候這樣富航鬥薑
that family is too famous
那一家是太有名的
i won't talk to my wife
我不會跟我太太
I'll just drive there
我就開車過去
Fu Hang Dou Jiang
上個富航鬥薑
long time no go
很久沒去
I want to say, of course you can, line up for people to come.
我想說 當然可以 排隊排到人家來了
Hehehe, let me tell him, forget it
呵呵呵 我跟他講 算了算了
So that's so famous, so famous
所以那家太有名了 太有名了
Think about it, maybe we can provide it
你想想看 搞不好我們可以提供了
That is, which one do you think can make a lot of money?
就是說 你認為哪一家 搞不好賺很多錢
Maybe you check everyone
搞不好你每個人去查
Everyone is going to be a baking cup
每個人都去 當個烙杯啊這樣
go look it up go look it up he said
去查一下 去查他說
If you find out, for example, you can get a commission before the lecture
假如查到的話 比如說講前你就可以抽成
For example, I don't know when I was a child
譬如說 這樣的話 我不知道小時候
Will it? There may be a problem with this, that is,
會不會 這個可能有一個問題就是說
Will there be any missing complaints? Into the insult experiment
會不會有些什麼遺失抱怨 入侮實驗
He just gives it to you, to you, to you, which is a bit of a mess
他就是給你 給你 給你 等於是有點亂舉花
Then, for example, your family, I will
然後譬如說你這一家 我就
Anyway, seeing that you are very upset, I will report it to you.
反正看你很不爽 我就給你報
I said this family has tax evasion.
我說這一家有漏稅什麼樣
This has a related problem
這個有一個相關性的問題
But in terms of self-service design, it means
不過在自助設計上的話 就是說
For example, say something like this, for example, let
譬如說像這樣的話 譬如說讓
Everyone knows that, for example, there are a few that are not bad.
大家曉得說 譬如說有幾家是生也不錯的
This information can probably be grasped by adopting the purpose
採用目的大概就可以掌握到這個資訊
He can, because the Ministry of Finance is in the office, and he doesn't know
他就可以,因為財政部就在辦公室,他也不曉得
For example, if you compare several companies to make more money, the locals are probably small.
比如說拿幾家比較賺錢,當地人大概就小的
I mean maybe some, either the basic idea or the
我是說可能有些,不是說基本想法就是說
That is to say, a problem like this may require a very different idea to solve it
就是說像這樣的問題,可能要有一個很不同的想法來解決
Not like the traditional thinking, the traditional thinking
不是像傳統想法這樣,傳統想法這樣
Because this problem I think is a structural problem
因為這個問題我覺得是一個結構性的問題
It's not a matter of working hard or not
不是說努力不努力的問題
Like the American words I just said, one hundred yuan, fifty-seven yuan escaped
像我剛剛講的美國的話,一百塊,五十七塊逃脫掉
Like the US, it should be very strict.
像美國那個應該是很嚴的吧
So my basic idea is that maybe what I just mentioned is just a possible direction
所以我基本想法就是,可能我剛剛提的只是一個可能的一個方向
But maybe if you think about it, maybe it means
但是可能你們想想看,可能就是說
It means that you can put forward different ideas and different views
等於可以提出不同的想法,不同的看法
There is a common saying in Taiwan
我們臺灣有一句話很普遍
So long live Taiwan
所以要臺灣萬萬歲
So I ask Professor Yang to address this issue
所以請楊教授針對這個問題
your opinion
您的看法
Is it true that there are many inappropriate taxes in Taiwan?
是不是台灣有很多不適當被剋的稅
Otherwise, why is it called Taiwan Ten Thousand Tax?
要不然怎麼叫台灣萬萬稅
I don't think so
這個我就不大想
However, from the tax perspective
不過自從稅務的比重來看
Taiwan tax is very low
台灣稅務是很低的
you were just the first in front of us
你剛剛我們前面的第一個
From the point of view of tax ratio, the previous
前面那些從稅務比重來看的話
Suppose that in your capital
假如說你的總首都當中
Suppose you didn't do it last time
假如說你上次不搞了
with Ossie
跟歐西就
If you look at the single sale, it can reach forty
你看單賣的話到四十幾
Swedish words are more than fifty
瑞典的話是超過五十的
more than fifty
超過五十的
In other words, out of a hundred dollars
換句話說一百塊當中
Only high taxes are taken away
只有很高的稅務被拿走
but that is to say
但也是就是說
Maybe I now people want to have one
可能我現在民眾要有一個
It's like he thinks it's good
等於是他覺得這樣不錯
feel good
覺得這樣不錯
The silver merchants are also probably their service is also very good
銀商就是也是可能他們的服務也很好
I'm talking about the tax value
我講這個稅值的
Or everyone has a consensus like this
或是大家有個共識這樣
But Taiwan's biggest problem now is that
但台灣現在最大的問題就是說
If you want to pay him more taxes
你要給他多拿一點稅的話
not easy
不太容易
He will also first say that you show your efficiency
他也會先說你把你的效率表現出來
I remember when Chen Shui-bian first came up
我印象中當年陳水扁剛上來的時候
It wasn't that there was a Chen Dinglang
不是當時有一個陳定郎
he had an idea
他當時就有個想法
He said I must be very inefficient
他說這我一定很沒有效率
very inefficient
很沒有效率
He can save a lot if he comes up
假如他上來的話他就可以節省很多
But he came up and didn't solve anything
但他上來沒有解決什麼東西
So that problem is not equal to the fuselage alone
所以那個問題不是等於機身單單
also makes sense
也有道理
If you take money from others
從人家把錢拿去的話
Of course I want to see your performance
我當然要看到你的表現
Now our little one pays
現在我們小的繳了
so we don't know where to go
所以我們不曉得要到哪邊去
so i think another idea
所以我覺得有另外一個想法
It may be to try to introduce a market economy
可能是要盡量引進市場經濟
not necessarily
也說不一定
For example, to prove that all the services I provide can be sold
譬如說證我提供的服務都可以來賣
don't say free price
不要說無償的代價
If you sell it, you probably have one to shop around for.
你賣的話大概就有一個貨比三家
don't buy you
就不要買你啊
isn't he now
他現在不是嘛
now is forcing you to come
現在就是強迫你來
So maybe the people have to spend their money
所以可能要讓民眾泡出錢來
i understand that is to say
我了解就是說
Although the tax is very low
雖然稅很低
but what we just said
但是我們剛剛講的
Maybe not as low as I thought
可能也沒有想像那麼低
Maybe it's all the burden of the new place
可能都是新之所在負擔
but anyway
但不管怎麼樣的話
many people's thoughts
很多民眾的想法
I only know what a lot of people think
我只了解很多民眾的想法
that is
就是說
Your government is just not efficient so not so high
你政府就是沒有效率那麼沒那麼高
not that high
沒那麼高
how tall is it
是不是有多高
we don't know
我們不曉得
The efficiency of the government is of course relatively poor
政府的效率當然是比較差
probably can imagine
大概是可以想想到
Because it has more regulations
因為它規定比較多嘛
But the idea is to say
但這個想法就是說
When you want to take money from its pocket
你要從它口袋裡面拿錢的時候
I think the general public's thinking is that
我想一般民眾的想法就是說
Maybe this person takes money
搞不好這個人家拿錢
will still be wasted
還是會浪費掉
It's like not much help
等於是沒有多大幫助
as far as we know
據我們所認知的是
seems to be the same product
好像是同一個產品
more than once engraved water
不只刻一次水
engraved many times
就刻了很多次
just say it many times
就說罷了很多次
This is the business value tax
這是營業價值稅
like me
就像我這樣
He would have taken more classes
他本來就多接上課程
that should
那個應該
he is taxing part of your worth
他是對你的價值的部分課稅
I don't give you a lot of supplements
不是給你補很多品
No la
沒有啦
If he wants to come down and talk to the course
他想要走下來跟課程的話
he will make up
他就補
but he is divided
但是他是分
Partial class equal to this value
等於這個價值的部分課程
But overall far away
不過整體遙遠的話
His tax rate is actually not high
他的稅率實際上是不高
And the size of the government is not high
而且政府的規模也不高
compared with advanced countries
跟先進國家來比不高
And not only not high
而且不僅不高
and gradually falling
而且逐漸在下跌
so
所以
It's a special phenomenon
算是很特殊的現象
in other words
換句話說
The size of his government is compared with that of many countries
他的政府規模跟很多國家來比
are very low
都是很低的
The tax I pay is compared with many countries
我繳的稅跟很多國家來比
Not as high as imagined
沒有想像那麼高啦
no double taxation
沒有重複課稅的
Eh
欸
I don't know what you mean by double taxation
我不曉得你重複課稅有什麼意思
but
但是
Maybe not as high as I thought
可能沒有想像那麼高啦
Thanks
謝謝
come who
來 哪位
last introduction
最後一個介紹
Hello Mr. Yang
楊老師好
that is
就是
Just now Teacher Yang mentioned that
剛才楊老師有提到說
he
他
It's the one in Taiwan
就是目前我們台灣的那個
The gap between rich and poor has widened
貧富差距已經滿大的
If the portion of income tax that is being reduced today
如果說今天在減少的所得稅的部分
If the income is levied in the form of consumption tax
那以消費稅的方式來克徵那個所得的話
Will it lead to a wider gap between the rich and the poor?
會不會導致我們的貧富差距更擴大
Thank you, teacher
謝謝老師
I just said that I am not advocating a consumption tax instead of an income tax
我剛講過我倒沒有主張以消費稅來取代所得稅
i made no such claim
我沒有做這樣的主張
Because the consumption tax is only 5% now
因為現在消費稅也只有5%而已
Income tax is to let us know
所得稅是讓我們曉得
Some 40% and some 30% have
40幾% 30幾%都有
So to replace it, I think this should not be feasible
所以等於來取代它我覺得這個應該是不可行
And this is far from the traditional concept
而且這個跟傳統的觀念差太多了
Because the conventional wisdom is that an income tax is a better tax
因為傳統概念認為所得稅就是比較好的稅
Consumption tax is a US tax
消費稅就是一個美費稅
I just want to give you an impression that
我只是要給各位一個impression說
Income tax is not as good as we thought
所得稅沒有我們想像中那麼好
From the data point of view
從資料上來看
In terms of progress
從進步方面的事情來看
indeed there are
的確有
have a lot of questions
有很多問題
The temperature elimination tax may not be as bad as we thought
消溫稅可能沒有我們想像那麼差
it is not a regressive tax
它不是一個累退稅
My reasonable thought is that it should be a proportional tax
我比較合理的想法就是它應該是一個比例稅
proportional tax
比例稅
Is it possible to indirectly make up for the shortage of hand tax with the consumption tax
有沒有可能以消溫稅來間接補充手的稅的不足
it's just an idea
這只是一個想法而已
But the fundamental idea is to say
不過最根本的想法就是說
Negotiating the tax of hands is not as good as expected
談的手的稅沒有想像那麼好
So in fact the tax potential
所以在稅勢事實上
may have a whole new and different idea
可能要有一個全新不同的想法
new and different ideas
全新不同的想法
we know that health insurance costs
我們曉得那個健保費用
it receives a lot of tax
它就收到很多的稅
a lot of taxes
很多的稅收
We know what we thought
我們曉得當初的想法是什麼想法
The original idea was to say
當初的想法就是說
We know that the combined filing
我們曉得那個合併申報
Right
對吧
The original idea was when it was first proposed
當初的想法就是最早提出來的時候
The director at that time was Yang Shiliang
當時的那個處長是楊氏良
He argued that the total declaration
他就主張就是說總和申報
sum declaration
總和申報
sum declaration I felt that I was
總和申報我就覺得當時我就
Not a big war like this
不大戰爭這樣
This so-called tax itself has a large share
這個所謂的稅本身就有很大份
You are putting the responsibility of the new master, who has already paid a heavy tax
你等於讓新師傅的責,他本來就繳了很重的稅
You pay him again now, and pay for the combined insurance
你現在再繳他,再繳一次合併審保
Think about it, you have to file taxes twice a year
你想想看,你一年當中,你等於要申報兩次的稅
Pay this tax once for the general tax
一次為了一般的守的稅來繳這個稅
Another time for health insurance will be paid again, you see how many people
另外一次為了健保會再繳,你看這個多少名
And the tax you keep is not a good tax in the first place.
而且守的稅本來就不是很好的稅
He must have defended the old pine later
他後來一定要用古松保衛的方式
I don't know how you feel about Gu Song's way of defending
古松保衛的方式我不曉得各位感覺什麼樣
If I feel it myself, it seems that there is nothing special
我自己感覺的話,好像沒什麼特別感覺
Every year when I declare the tax I keep, it is a very painful thing for me
我每年在申報守的稅的時候,對我來說都很痛苦的一件事情
Because you pay a lot of taxes, you have to pay a lot of taxes
因為繳的稅特別多,你要繳很多稅
That would be very painful, it would be like asking you to say that
那就特別痛苦,等於讓你說那一陣子就
Because the payment is equal to the largest expenditure in the whole year, that's right
因為繳的等於是整年當中最大的一筆支出,就對了
Did you say that the health insurance association, I don’t feel anything special
那邊有沒有說,健保會的話,我覺得沒什麼特別感覺
But NHS finances are doing really well now
但健保局財務現在變得很不錯
Why is it good?
為什麼很不錯呢?
because he received a lot of taxes
因為他收到很多的稅收
How is this tax collected?
這個稅收怎麼收呢
That is, it has a wide range of tax machines
就是它稅機很廣
Tax machine is very wide
稅機很廣
anything is welcome
什麼東西都可以客
it has a discovery
它就有一個發現
It is the income that encourages customers to pay a lot of taxes
就是鼓勵的收入就客了很多的稅
Such a small sword board would have been based on the new hand
那麼小的劍板會本來是以新之手的為單位
its for new hands
它對於新之手
A tax on re-customers other than hands
以外的手的再客一個稅
other than novice
以外的新之手的以外的
For example, to encourage
譬如說鼓勵
it receives a lot of tax
它就收到很多的稅收
another one
另外一個
it has another major discovery what is
它有另外一個重大的發現是什麼
The major discovery is that
重大的發現就是說
Taiwan is under the original health care system
台灣在原先的健保之度底下
The ones held by new hands are much lower
抱的新之手的都偏低很多
much lower
偏低很多
So it then says
所以它後來就是說
the part that doesn't hug you
對你沒有抱的那一部分
I will pay you an extra tax now
我現在額外跟你客一個稅
it saw a huge increase in revenue
它就發現收入大大增加
So now health insurance
所以現在健保級
it is financially
它就財務上
look what happened not long ago
你看前不久還發生什麼
Are you hugging someone and saying that your finances are bad?
有沒有在抱人說財務不好
good income now
現在的收入很不錯
right
是吧
arrive
到就
Take a little from middle, take a little from C, I will engrave two pieces for you for 100 yuan
中拿一點,C拿一點,就100塊給你刻個兩塊
do you feel it
你有沒有感覺?
may not feel much
可能不大有感覺
It is a little bit eastward, but it has a lot of taxes
東刻一點,但是它稅金很廣啊
Very wide, you see, everyone in Taiwan only needs to pay one yuan
很廣,你看,台灣每個人只要繳一塊錢的
What can you earn?
就可以收入什麼?
More than 20 million
兩千多萬
Because there are 23 million people
因為有兩千三百萬人嘛
You have to pay a dime, everyone pays a dime
你要繳一毛錢,每個人繳一毛錢
You have an income of more than 20 million
你就有兩千多萬的收入
Think about it, if you pay 100 yuan to 100 yuan per person
你想想,繳100塊到每個人繳100塊的話
So its tax is very wide, very wide
所以它稅金很廣,很廣
It draws a big circle, which is completely different from what it thinks is loud
它就畫一大圈,跟它當作響亮,完全不一樣
When it actually does, it doesn't complain now
它真正去做的時候,它現在都沒有什麼抱怨
it says my taxes are fine
它說我稅收很不錯
It says finances are getting cheap money
它說財務越來越賤錢
So that system, I think we might know
所以那個制度,我覺得搞不好我們曉得
There is a very important principle when collecting taxes
收稅的時候有一個很重大一個原則
I hope it's forehead hair will be the same so that it won't feel pain
希望把它的額毛一樣,讓它不會感覺到痛
like i said every year when the role, i'm in pain
像我說每年角色的時候,我就很痛苦
Did you pluck too much forehead hair that time?
那一次拔得太多額毛了嘛
I feel very uncomfortable
我就感覺到很不爽的
i'm there every day
我就每天在那裡
my feet are so broken
我腳這麼碎多
Especially considering that many people
特別想到有很多人都
hands earn more money than me
手比我多賺的錢
Broken feet, less than me, etc.
腳都碎了比我少等等
very upset
就很不爽
But at the health insurance meeting
但在健保會上
I believe you all feel nothing
我相信各位都沒什麼感覺
because he buckles
因為他就東扣西扣
come here for a smoke
來這裡抽一點
carve a little there
那裡刻一點
But he has a lot of taxes
但是他稅金很廣
tax is very wide
稅金很廣
like i said
就像我講的
23 million people
有2,300萬人
Only one foot per person
每人只要腳一塊
just one dollar
一塊錢就好
right
對
He collected a bunch
他就收了一堆
tantamount to tax design
等於是在稅制設計上
I think to think very differently
我覺得要很不同的想法
Professor Yang Hello, Mr. Yang
楊教授 楊老師好
i want to ask two questions
我想請問兩個問題
that is
就是說
Professor Yang just mentioned
楊教授剛好提到
part of the lock tax
鎖得稅的部分
The country's locked tax areas are divided into
那有國的鎖得稅區分為
Lock in the tax payment period during the silver interest period
銀利時期鎖得稅跟
Personal comprehensive lock-in tax
個人綜合鎖得稅
That
那
Professor Yang here is mainly for
楊教授這邊是主要針對
Personal comprehensive lock-in tax
個人綜合鎖得稅裡面的
real class lock
實類鎖得
One of the new locks
其中之一的新之鎖得
Does it mean that this new lock is
是不是代表說這個新之鎖得
Why compared with the consumption tax
之所以跟消費稅比較具有
If this is compared with consumption tax
這個跟消費稅比較的話
relatively representative
比較具有代表性
The second question is
那第二個問題就是說
In the past, our country focused on the income tax
我國在之前的時候針對所得稅這一塊
That's when the minimum tax was introduced
就是那時候提出最低稅負制
What about the minimum tax system
對那最低稅負制的話
As Professor Yang said
就如同楊教授所說的
It's just that he's not included in the property tax.
就是他並沒有納入財產稅
It's the property
就是財產這一塊
If it is included in the property
那如果納入財產這一塊
to the minimum tax system
到最低稅負制的話
will that follow
那會不會跟
because i'm not partisan
因為我沒有黨派的色彩
I wonder if that will affect the vote
我想說那會不會影響到選票
You want to take money from the people
你那個要從民眾中中拿錢
I don't think that's a big deal for everyone.
大家都我想這個都不大感
Moreover, there is a county in Taiwan that says that it often increases the price
而且台灣有個縣鄉說往往加碼
not only not from you
不僅不從你身上來
He also lowered your taxes
他還給你降低稅
give you a lot of benefits
給你很多的福利
No, you want to say that every year when the election
沒有 你想說每年選舉的時候
The old man is overweight today
老人今天都加碼
Because, for example, the U.S. dollar factory overweight
因為比如說美金廠加碼
The KMT will continue to increase
國民黨那也要繼續加碼
but take money from you
但從你身上拿錢
I think ordinary politicians don't dare to speak.
我想一般政客的話都不大敢
not quite dare
不大敢
So what you said earlier
所以你前面所說的那一點
I don't think so
我覺得應該不是
My point just says
我的point只是說
RSS
台灣的首俄社
what we just compared
我們剛剛比較的話
For example, compared with European and American countries
比如說跟歐美國家來比
Like the United States, probably
像美國的話大概
The new system of the first Russia probably accounted for 60
新制首俄大概是占到60
About 56. more
大概56.多
Other capitals are about 48
其他首俄大概是48
in other words
換句話說
The European Xi Jinping Country in Europe
歐洲的那個歐裔習近國
But Taiwan's words accounted for 75
但台灣的話占到75
means
就表示
from a certain point of view
某種角度來看的話
It means that other capitals have not grasped
就表示說其他首俄沒有掌握到
Because of the words you have mastered in other countries
因為你其他首俄掌握到的話
The new system of the first Russia will not account for so high
新制首俄就不會占到那麼高
Because Taiwan accounts for 75%
因為台灣占到75%
even quite high
甚至蠻高
Compared with the data of those countries
比起那些國家的資料來看
high
高
means equal to other Russian
就表示等於其他首俄
not mastered well
沒有掌握得很好
That makes you a new system of the first Russia
才使得你新制首俄
75% of your tax return
在你的報稅資料中占到75%
so
所以
Didn't say what happened to other capitals
並沒有說其他首俄怎麼樣
i just say
我只是說
General impression of Taiwan
台灣的一般的印象
The general impression is that
一般的印象就是說
Taiwan's personal broken hands seem to be broken minds
台灣的個人手頭碎好像是心智手頭碎
From the data point of view, this concept
這個概念從資料上來看
not necessarily completely wrong
也不見得是完全不對的
Because compared to other countries
因為跟其他國家來比的話
It is indeed flat
的確是平高的
Ye Ping Gao
也平高
Master Yang Liao
那個楊廖師
I
我
When Taiwan was broken, there was a lot of loss
台灣那個碎的時候流失很大
Simplest central government
最簡單的中央政府
What about that water bottle?
那顆水瓶就把什麼
Inheritance tax, what kind of property tax can be lowered for him
遺產稅 什麼財產稅隨便給他降低
Did you talk about the Japanese one at that time?
那當時你有沒有談到日本那個
say clothing
說服飾
In fact, Taiwan also has
其實台灣也有
Taiwan also has
台灣也有
I worked in a trading company before retiring from a trading company
我在貿易公司退休之前在貿易公司上班
all of that Taiwan
那個台灣的所有這些
to what extent do you capitalize me
你資本我導致什麼程度
he has the tax office
他有那個稅增處
So he has the thermostat tube
所以他有化溫那個管器
Just the latest newspaper, etc.
就現在最近那個報紙等等
He gave me a pipe for the police
他給刑警給我管器
But the clothes are very busy
但是說服飾都很忙
He usually doesn't come just to check taxes
他平常不到光是來查稅
Honglian was puzzled when he came
他來的時候就紅蓮不解
I'll check it out, Honglian will only come during the holidays
會來查 紅蓮過節才會來
He was not happy during the investigation
那查的時候他一不高興喔
We have rules, you
我們有規定嘛 你這個
All the corner tax certificates are related to our car
所有的角稅證明跟我們那個汽車
What about taxation, he helps beauties want to save Qilian
排照稅什麼 他有助美人要保存七連嘛
Then you are now in the 103rd year of the Republic of China
那你現在是民國103年
He can say sorry
他可以講說 對不起喔
We have a problem with your 98 year old one
我們對你那個98年那個有問題啊
From July 31st to October 31st in 1998
你從那個98年來7月31號到10月31號
Where can you show me? The company will hire two floats
哪來給我看 那公司就要請兩部花彩車
Then go to the state-owned machinery, because our company's
再到那個國設機器 因為我們公司那個
The business volume is 2 billion US dollars, let's go there
營業的美金20億啊 再過去啊
OK OK OK so yes that's another point this
OK OK OK 所以對 那另外一點喔 這個
Because Taiwan is encouraging others, for example
因為台灣在鼓勵人家 譬如說
There is a joke that you just pick up the business card like someone else
有個笑話說 你就接上像人家拿那個名片啦
Three times out of ten, Zhang said the chairman or general manager
十張裡面有三次張說董事長或總經理
I have many friends who are doing this trade
我很多朋友他們在做這個貿易
Others can also apply for this trade
其他人也是可以申請這個貿易
Maoyu license, there are really regulations
貓羽執照,那真有規定
Your cat feather license company gives you
你這個貓羽執照公司給你
If you have no business activities within three years, it will be canceled
你三年內你沒有營業行為它會注銷
but i really can't find a business what to do
但是我真的找不到生意怎麼辦
I don't want to log out
我又不要注銷
Because there are many advantages to not having to log out.
因為沒有注銷都有的好處很多嘛
like the one in my kids house now
就像現在我的孩子家中那個
interior designer
室內裝潢設計師
he has a license
他有申請執照
His motorcycle family can reimburse
他的摩托車家有可以報帳
Is 40,000 a treat?
4萬是不是請客
Is it possible to report on business behavior?
是不是營業行為也可以報
Report that execution?
報那個執出嘛
then my own motorcycle
那我自己摩托車
I'm going to do my best
我自己要加油
My car owner wants to refuel himself
我的車主自己要加油
this is unfair
這個是不公平
So it shouldn't let you discount it
所以這一點它就不應你把它折照掉
then what should we do
那怎麼辦呢
just looking for friends
就是找朋友
yours
你的那個
expanded to
擴大到啦
Even if the days come, the photos will not be lost
都來日子照也不會掉
Just use my name to ship
就用我的名義去出貨
yes
是
So this kind of encouragement
所以這樣的鼓勵人家
unfair tax system
不公平的稅制嘛
yes
是
So your tax system
所以你那個稅制
say you are in hong kong
說你在香港
In particular, there are many correct ways to set it up
尤其是設定它有很多正確方法可以科徵
But just like this, the east factory and the west factory are all empty
但就這樣來東廠一點西廠都廠光
Because it should be said that the reform of the sky should be more important than the reform of words
因為應該是說天之應該是改革比說字改革更重要
yes
是
Thanks
謝謝
As you mentioned, it means that everyone should know each other in terms of academic qualifications.
像你提出來也是等於在學歷上大家要認識
In fact, a Policy cannot be decoupled from its implementation
一個Policy事實上跟它的執行面是不能脫鉤的
You can't say I only talk about one Policy
你不能說我只談一個Policy
but did not talk about an implementation issue
但沒有談到一個執行面的問題
For example, I just talked about a tax matter
譬如說我剛剛談一個稅務事
when i just listened to him
我剛剛聽他講的時候
I feel good listening to my classmate
聽我那個同學講感覺到不錯
but what you just said
但你剛剛講的話
Whether the tax affairs are good or not will lead to other issues
稅務事好不好就延伸出其他的問題出來
for example
譬如說
So it is equivalent to a lot of times, it is a policy
所以等於是很多時候的話就是一個政策
when implementing a policy
推行一個政策的時候
Can't be decoupled from your executive plane
不能跟你的執行面脫鉤
It performs very inefficiently
它在執行效率很低
For example, the boss of your company
比方說你弄的公司老闆
It stipulates that you can't buy a car for more than 2 million
它規定你買車子不能超過200萬
Suppose you exceed 2 million
假如說你超過200萬
He will ratify you to 2 million
他就追認你到200萬
But the 2 million will be included in that asset
但這200萬要列入那個資產
In the list of sales assets
銷貨資產的列表裡面
He has a rule of forty percent
他有規定百分之四十
So if our car exceeds 2 million
所以我們這個車子超過200萬的話
forty percent
百分之四十的話就是
800,000 in me
我裡面的80萬
I can pay taxes this year
我今年就可以課稅
Then I will divide it into 10 years
那其他來我就分成10年
Everyone can take lessons
每人可以課
but we didn't
但是我們沒有
If there is no such thing as a job, there is no salary
當工沒有這個沒有工資的話
I bought that Yirong Zheqi 800,000
我買個那個義容哲氣80萬
i don't have a dime
我一毛錢都沒有
he pays for himself
他自己負擔
So this implementation aspect is really
所以這個執行方面真的是
It's more important than you to reform a little bit
比你稍微去改革更重要
a friend of mine just said
我一個朋友就是說
sometimes taiwan
有時候台灣
The best day in Taiwan is to say
在台灣最好的日子就是說
start your own company
你自己開一個公司
It's big to report to work after eating
吃完了都報工算大
Reporting a job is a big deal
報工算大
He said that this day in Taiwan
他說台灣這個日子
will have a good time
會過得蠻不錯的
Of course he has rules
當然他有規定的
you this
你這個
look at him
看他一邊
do you sometimes guess one
有時候會猜一件嗎
I talked about
我講到
i think in general
我想總的來說
If we look at the system in terms of money received
如果我們從收到的錢來看這個制度的話
of course
那當然
The second-generation health insurance supplementary insurance fee is a lot of money
二代健保補充保險費是收的不少錢
But he actually received the most
但是他其實收的最多的
Not the non-earn income part
不是non-earn income這部分
It's already paid for this
而是就已經繳的這個
This part of the so-called seller income
這個所謂的seller income這個部分
because he has this
因為他有這個
In particular there is an insured salary scale
特別是有一個投保薪資分級表
The upper limit of the grading table is more than 180,000
那分級表上限是18萬以上的
no class at all
統統都沒有課
what about this part
那這個部分呢
you don't have class
你個人不課
but your boss wants to pay for you
但是你的老闆要幫你付
so this part
所以這個部分
let's just say
我們隨便說
That's 300,000 a month
就是一個月30萬嘛
Then you have 120,000 of this money
那你有12萬的這個錢
yourself
你自己
did not pay insurance premiums
沒有交保險費
But the boss wants to help you pay this money every month
但是老闆要每個月幫你交這個錢
this money adds up
這個錢加起來
The second-generation health insurance supplementary premium was overcharged by 400
二代健保補充保險費多收了400
Probably received 43 billion
大概是收了430億
just this part
光是這個部分
The boss has more than 20 billion talents
老闆天賦就已經200多億了
In fact, the money that encouragement actually accounts for is not much.
其實鼓勵其實佔的那個錢其實是不多的
for encouraging him to have another
因為鼓勵他又有一個
Everyone would know if they knew
大家如果知道的話就知道
5000 yuan
5000塊
That is, there is no class below 5,000 yuan.
就是這個5000塊以下是不課的
So now a lot of interest is splitting bills
所以現在很多的利息在拆單
Disassembled to say less than 5,000 yuan
拆到說不到5000塊
So now we need to amend the law
那所以現在要修法
It is the annual settlement
就是全年結算
that is
就是
avoid this part
避免掉這個部分
because too smart
因為太聰明了
everyone is evading taxes
大家都在逃稅
We always blame the government
我們常常都罵政府
But we are smart enough to say
但是我們又自己聰明到說
we will follow
我們自己來跟
this government
這個政府
He's pretending like we're here to play this
他做裝我們好像來玩這個
game
遊戲
So actually
所以其實
talking about the whole system
在談這個整個的制度
I just came to a conclusion that I think is very good
剛剛有一個結論我覺得非常的好
that is
就是說
ideal or
理想或者是
system
制度
But this executive level
可是這個執行層面
if with some twist
如果有一些扭曲的話
It's not just that it can't hit the target
它其實不單是打不到目的
And it will greatly discount this fairness
而且會讓這個公平性大大折扣
that's all
以上
then you check me to find out what's there
那你檢查我去查有什麼
that is
就是
It was said in the news before
之前新聞有說
The rich in France are just dissatisfied with the way France treats them
法國的富人就是不滿法國對他們科
The heavier income tax or other taxes
比較重的那個所得稅或是其他的稅
So I immigrated to Singapore directly.
所以就直接移民到新加坡的
If our taxes are getting fairer
如果說我們的稅是越來越公平
But our powerful entrepreneurs
但是我們有實力的企業家
or have the strength to create
或是說有實力創造
If the high-level people run away
高層的人跑掉的話
Isn't it bad for our country?
對我們國家不是很虧嗎
of course it is
當然是啦
So that means
所以就是說
like us people
就像我們這些人
That's the way to say it.
就這樣就講來講比較有辦法啦
It's not so easy for you to tax him
你要課他到稅不是那麼容易
From a theoretical point of view
在學理上來看的話
That is to say, from the point of view of efficiency
就是說從效率觀點來看的話
That is to say, for those incomes with relatively high liquidity
就是說對於這些流動性比較高的那些所得
The tax rate would have been lower
稅率本來就要比較低一點
From the point of view of efficiency
從效率觀點來上
less efficient
效率比較低一點
So overall
所以整體來說的話
like i said taiwan has some structural problems
就像我說台灣有些結構性的問題
You have a lot of companies in China
你在中華企業特別多
Then teach the rich man
然後對那有錢人課
So it's not as easy as we imagined
所以不是我們想像這麼容易啦
It's not that we have to deal with those language people
不是說我們就要對那些語言人
We say positive education income you don't pay taxes
我們說正面教育所得你沒有繳稅
so i will tax you
所以我就給你課稅
This is theoretically more fair and just
這是理論上是比較公平正義的
Because you have income, you don't have to pay taxes
因為本來有所得就不要繳稅
but when actually doing
但真正在做的時候
not as easy as we imagined
不是我們想像那麼容易
Look at the tax reduction in our text last time
你看我們上次那個正文稅數減少
But the economy as a whole has also become worse
但是整個經濟也變得比較差
So this means
所以這個就是說
This is a structural problem
這個是一個結構性的問題
It's not that you're rich
不是說你有錢人課
So you sleep with heavier feet
所以你比較腳比較重的睡
not so simple
不是那麼簡單
may have a whole new and different idea
可能要有一個全新不同的想法
new and different ideas
全新不同的想法
structural issues like these
像這些結構性的問題
How about a new idea for you
怎麼樣你一個新的idea
New idea to engrave this problem
新的想法來刻似這個問題
instead of just saying how about fairness and justice
而不是說只是說為了公平正義怎麼樣
like you just said
就像你剛剛所說的
These people run away when you're there
你刻刻的時候這些人逃掉
Not good for Taiwan market
對台灣市場也沒什麼好處
It's like losing both
等於是兩敗俱傷
so this should
所以這個要
really want one
真的要有一個
It was a whole new and different idea
本來是一個全新不同的想法
come to ask a question
來請教一個問題
That is to say, just at the beginning
就是說剛剛一開始講
A school of economics in the United States is
在美國的某經濟學院是
he thinks
他是認為
He said the most drastic way is to say
他是提最激烈的辦法就是說
Tax that should be expected with consumption tax
應該用消費稅來期待說的稅
And if I remember correctly
然後我如果記憶沒錯的話
Asked whether the director was with me at the time
跟所長當時是在不在我這兒
He said that Hong Kong seemed to be in a certain period
他說香港好像在某一個時期
very short period
很短的時期
implemented this method
實施過這個辦法
Of course, because there are so many objections to legal persons
當然因為反對法人非常多
There is no Xi Jinping who said to change his father's explanation
就沒習近平 說改自己爸爸說明
So I'm going to ask two questions
所以我要問兩個問題
I don't know, subsidy chief, you don't have subsidy at this time.
我不知道 補助長 你這時候沒有補助
No
沒有啊
You subsidize first because I'm going to talk and I'm coming to an end
你先補助 因為我要講 我就要結束了
to finish
要問完
I think because of the change in the last year
我想 因為在去年一年的說改
Actually on this question
對這個問題其實
Discuss with each other many times
互相討論 都有很多次吧
I don't think there's a definitive answer to this
我想這個沒有一個定論
But we also recite many times
但是我們也背了很多次
I think this consumption tax is in Taiwan
我想這個消費稅在台灣
With Yang Jiahong, we are on the low side
跟在於楊家宏坦的我們是偏低
improve this direction
提高這個方向
yes but
對 但是
For some scholars, it is hoped that
針對於有些學者是希望說
consumption tax can be substituted for all
能夠用消費稅來替代所的
So this is controversial
所以這個是大家有爭議
And with reservations
而且有保留
No country in the world does this
就全世界也沒有任何一個國家這樣做
Then I want to follow the direction of Yang Jiahong
那我想跟在於楊家宏體的這個方向
all right but
都對 但是
When designing this tax system, many
很多在設計這個稅制的時候
has his first challenge
有他先舉的挑戰
For example, when he was working, the concept of lifetime income and consumption
比如說他幹的時候 終身所得消費的概念
It is perfectly feasible in a closed economic system
在一個封閉性的經濟體系是完全可行的
But as he just said
但是就如同他剛才講的
The broken locks are also difficult to grow
鎖的碎碎也很難長
I believe GST is also somewhat difficult to sleep on
我相信消費稅在某種程度也很難長臥
Why
為什麼
A Taiwanese is a small open geographic system
一個台灣人是小型開放地理體系
what i just said
我剛才講的
My family eats, drinks and has fun abroad
我家吃喝玩樂都在國外
May I ask how can I go to the class to pay the GST?
請問我怎麼有辦法去課到消費稅
So this part is actually not conclusive
所以這一部分其實沒有定論
But basically Taiwan's consumption tax
但是基本上台灣的消費稅
the lowest in the world
在全世界是最低的
So we ended up saying that we can slightly increase the
所以我們到最後就說能夠稍微調高
But you make up some of the tax deficit
但是你補一些手的稅不足
but to completely replace
但是要完全替代
we are law abiding
我們是有守法的
Thanks
謝謝
we're going to ask a very simple question
我們要請教一個很簡單的問題
that is
就是
Because we can't read the whole proposal to change
因為我們把整個建議書都讀不好去變
I have the impression that this idea also appeared in our report
我印象中這個idea也出現在我們的報告書
yes
是
Has it attracted the attention of any fiscal and taxation unit?
有沒有引起任何財稅單位的重視
Indonesia knows
印尼所知
From what I understand now, this shouldn't be the point
我的了解現在這個應該不是重點
now is not the point
現在不是重點
Now the Ministry of Finance is real estate
現在財政部是房地產
he is a focus now
他現在是一個重點
But it's like raising the tax
不過等於是要提高這個稅的話
I think the general public is against it
我想一般民眾都反對
Therefore, the main reason is that it is generally recognized that
所以主要理由是一般都認定
GST is a split tax
消費稅是一個裂退稅
so you see
所以你看
like in five percent executive yuan
像在百分之五的行政院
He can skip the legislature
他可以不要經過立法院
He can directly increase to 7
他就可以直接調高到7
Because of the rules he can turn it up to 10
因為規定的話他可以調高到10
But he was not moved at all
但他都一點不感動
why not touched at all
為什麼一點不感動
It's obviously not an easy thing to do
很顯然是不太容易的一件事情
not easy thing
不太容易的一件事情
Because it is generally believed that the consumption tax is a split tax
因為一般認為消費稅就是一個裂退稅
disadvantageous to the poor
對窮人是比較不利的
as long as you are one
你只要一體的話
or
或是
Right now it means he's turning it up by 5 to 10
目前就是說他調高5到10
He doesn't have to go through the legislature
他是不必經過立法院的
but he was not moved
但他都不感動
not moved
不感動
He is not even moved by 5 to 6
他連5到6他都不感動
It means that if the tax is raised, it will be very loud.
就表示這個稅調高的話是很有聲音
And when you turn it up, think about it
而且調高之後你想想看
I imagine the prices will be raised as well.
我想像到物價就一定也會調高
The whole will also be raised
整個也會調高
Because this increase is a bit similar to the preferential price of water and electricity.
因為這個調高就有點類似水電會優價這樣
turn this up
這個調高
So this is tuned up
所以這個調高
Like Japan, hasn't he recently raised his voice?
像日本他最近不是調高嗎
is good in the short run
是好在短期上來看
he has a big problem
他就有很大的一個問題
Long term is of course more difficult to say
長期當然就比較難講
is good in the short term
是好在短期上
And what he said at the time
而且他當時調高的話
is through how big a
是透過多大的一個
tantamount to the opposition
等於是反對黨
Democratic Party
當時政民黨
agree with the ruling party
跟執政黨同意
The ruling party later stepped down
執政黨後來就下台了
equal to somewhat equal to
等於是有點等於是
The ruling party was then
執政黨當時等於是
Promise to do this
Promise這樣做
that cost a lot
那個要付出很大的代價
This price means
這個代價就是說
If you turn it up, I'll let you step down
你調高我就讓你下台了
this has to pay
這個要付出
But Japan is a bit forced
不過日本等於是有點不得不然
has come to a point where it doesn't
已經到了一個不這樣做的話
far from enough
差遠就不夠
have to
不得不然
but he is also
不過他也是
was one equal to one
當時是一個等於是一個
It means that at that time the Prime Minister already had a
等於是那時候首相他已經有一個
It's like having a jig dance
等於是有一個捷舞
Just improve this and I probably won't be selected.
就提高這個我就大概選不上了
that result
那個結果
So the Prime Minister at that time did what he did, I think it was the same.
所以當時那個首相他這樣做我覺得也是
is also full
也是滿
fruitful
滿果絕的啦
you see Taiwan now you see
你看台灣現在你看
You don't have to tune up by force show
你不必透過力表演調高
everyone dare not come
大家都不敢到
because you turn up the words
因為你調高的話
This will be with water
這個就跟水定會
turn up the same
調高一樣
This is bound to have serious consequences
這個一定會帶來嚴重的後果
so everyone
所以大家
dare not do
不太敢做
So what I thought of was
所以我想到的就是
There may be a way is
可能有一個辦法就是
Will raising this will lower the tax for new makers?
調高這個是不是能夠降低新制手的稅
there is one
就有一個
Having an equal is having an advantage like this
有一個等於是有一個好處這樣
Turn it up here
這邊把調高
But the new samurai tax brought it down like this
但新制手的稅把它降低這樣
Put it all together
綜合一下
Perhaps the public may be more aware
可能民眾可能會比較清楚
You only want to raise this, I think this
你單單調高這個我才想這個
I probably don't have it easy
我大概不太容易
not feasible these days
這日子上不太可行
not feasible
不太可行
our time is almost up
我們時間差不多了
US tax is a very difficult problem
我們稅是一個非常困難的問題
There are many problems with this tax in Taiwan
那台灣的這個稅存在很多問題
very low on the one hand
一方面非常低
because I study history
因為我是研究歷史的
The ratio of our current tax ratio
我們現在稅的這個比例比
tomorrow
明天就
Even lower than in the Qing Dynasty
跟清朝一般的時候還要低
so it's a big problem
所以這是一個很大問題
But on the one hand, there are many people who do not pay taxes
可是一方面又有很多人稅收不到
On the other hand, the country has no money to spend
二方面 另外一方面國家又沒有錢可以用
Every year, as Teacher Yang said
每年如楊老師講的
Two to three hundred billion less
少兩三千億
Of course the one just mentioned
當然剛剛那個提到
The government randomly lowered it by two or three hundred billion
政府隨便亂降 降了兩三千億
These questions are very
這些問題都非常
And the treaty is very difficult
而條約非常之難
So what about today, Professor Yang will give us a detailed explanation from the beginning
那麼今天呢 楊教授給我們細說從頭
give us a very clear explanation
給我們一個非常清楚的解釋
very good speech
非常精采的演講
thank him thank you
謝謝他 謝謝各位